<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>William Alablasters [sic] seuen motuies [sic]. Remoued and confuted by Iohn Racster.</title>
            <title>Booke of the seven planets</title>
            <author>Racster, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 156KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B15438</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837996_2352</idno>
  <idno type="VID">2352</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2264226418</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 20601.5</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S102199</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99837996e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B15438)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2352)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1002:9, 1823:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>William Alablasters [sic] seuen motuies [sic]. Remoued and confuted by Iohn Racster.</title>
                  <title>Booke of the seven planets</title>
                  <author>Racster, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[88] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Peter Short for Andrew Wise dwelling in Paules Church-yard at the signe of the Angell,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1598.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Another issue, with cancel title page printed as M4, of: Racster, John.  A booke of the seven planets.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 20601 on UMI microfilm reel 1002.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-M⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the original in the Harvard University. Library.</note>
                  <note>Appears at reel 1002:9 (identified as STC 20601), and at reel 1823 ⁵ (both Harvard University Library. copy).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Alabaster, William, 1567-1640. --  Seven motives.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2352:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2352:1"/>
            <p>WILLIAM ALABLASTERS SEVEN MOTVIES.</p>
            <p>Remoued and confuted by <hi>John Racster.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Meliùs est claudicare in via quam currere extra viam.</hi> Agust.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>a snake coiled around a cross with hands shaking below</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>AT LONDON, Printed by <hi>Peter Short</hi> for <hi>Andrew Wise</hi> dwelling in Paules Church-yard at the signe of the Angell. 1598.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2352:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2352:2"/>
            <p>A BOOKE OF THE SE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VEN PLANETS, <hi>OR,</hi> Seuen wandring Motiues, of <hi>William Alablasters wit,</hi> Retrograded or remoued, by <hi>John Racster.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Meliùs est claudicare in via quam currere extra viam.</hi> August.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>crest with a book and the sun</figDesc>
               <p>VERITAS TVA ET VSQVE AD NUBES</p>
            </figure>
            <p>AT LONDON, Printed by <hi>Peter Short</hi> for <hi>Andrew Wise,</hi> dwelling in Paules Church-yard at the signe of the Angell. 1598.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:2352:3"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                  <p>HONI SOYT QVY MAL Y PENSE</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:2352:3"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable, <hi>Robert</hi> Earle of <hi>Essex</hi> and <hi>Ewe,</hi> Earle Marshall of England, Viscount Hereford and Bourgcher, Lorde Ferrers of Chartley, Bourgcher, and Loue in: and knight of the most noble order of the Garter: Master of her Maiesties Horse, and of the Ordinance: Chancelor of the Vniuersity of Cambridge, and one of her highnesse most honorable priuy Counsell.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He occurrents of three que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stions, beeing first aunswered from the mouth of their natiue causes, I hope (Right Honorable) that my poore paines shal finde this rich fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, that the truth yeelding it selfe to be their clyent, your honour will vouchsafe to become their Patron. And because the language of al questions is not alike; some demanding, some commanding, some obiecting, some vpbrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, some complaining, some controuling, some one way, some another, I will set down their seueral tunes, and tones as they spake vnto me. The first questions complaint (grieued to be dislodged before fully setled vpon the tast of discontentment) is:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> what necessitie causeth the Remoue of these motiues? The cause aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swereth, the hurt &amp; danger accompanying them. The hurt is manifest: for as in the bodie the increase of proud flesh is the decay of the sounde: So the spirit of
<pb facs="tcp:2352:4"/>popery (fed with vaine wandrings, and wandring va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of many of our wanton wits wanting grace) as it in the grouth of pride winneth ground in the body of this land: so the wholesome doctrine of true religion is turned tenant out of dores, to the great hurt of the whole realme, and the vtter vndoing of many. And therefore small need there is of these Motiues, when we our selues many of vs, helped that way by our own corruption, moue already down the hil to our destruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But rather great necessity haue wee to remoue thē, and to stay our steps before y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> break-necke of truth and true religion befall vnto vs. Againe, as the hurt is manifest, so is the daunger euident: For as a stumbling blocke vnto the blinde, so these Motiues crossing the way of the simple, will cause them to stumble and fall. Besides this, the change of Common-wealths is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued by the learned to come, not from fortune; for that is idle and prophane: nor from any fatall periode or reuolution of the stars; for that is but an astronomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call fancy: neither yet wholy from the maners of men and their dispositions; for that is but a philosophicall coniecture: But especially, it beginneth with y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> change of religion; for that is a theologicall rule. And it is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by many of note, that there sildome hath beene ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with vs, or else where in Christendom, any altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of gouernment, but some notorious hereticks, or schismatickes haue gone before, as signes and tokens of troubles already begun in the Church, and immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent dangers eftsoones insuing vpon the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth. And therefore very necessary it is for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruation of the peace of both states, to remooue the fewell of these flames, and to stop the gap or fill vp the breach whereat the enemy laboreth to get in vnto vs.
<pb facs="tcp:2352:4"/>This complaint of discontent ended and aunswered, the expostulation of vnkindnes in the second question rubbeth yet harder vpon me.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Admit it bee needfull to remoue these Motiues: yet what need I of all other to take the matter so haynously, and to busie my selfe more then needes? my answere. First it was not meet for any of our stronger champions, to enter the listes against so weak an enemy: for so he might get greater credit by being ouercome, then we glory by ouercom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming: the aduersaries mouth beeing still full of lies in their owne praise, with the open throat of vaine glory crying out, that their punies were able to hould plea with our ancients. Secondly, <hi>inter minores theologos,</hi> (if the authour be not quoted amisse) my selfe in many respects as fit as any to answere this quarrell.
<note place="margin">Westminster. Cambridge. Trinity Coll. D. <hi>Still</hi> now B. of Bath and Welles.</note> For the same schoole bred vs both, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same Vniuersity nourced vs both, the same colledge maintained vs both, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same master preferred vs both, the same roofe, nay the same bed somtimes contained vs both. Euery one wherof (as it is the lot of bankerupts to drowne others in their decay) haue lost somthing by his fal. The school saith, I haue lost my hope of him; the Vniuersity saith, I haue made shipwracke of my fauour in him; the colledge faith, I haue cast away my maintenance vpon him; the maister saith, I haue preferred preferment to discredit by him; the lodging saith his roome, the bed saieth his ease was euilly bestowed. For the recouery of which losses, if my slender gifts may any way comfort them, I thought it my duty in the behalfe of the schoole, V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuersitie, colledge, master, and the rest, to make some shewe of them to the view of the worlde: that it may perceiue and iudge (apt enough otherwise to iudge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misse) that all birdes be not blacke because the Crowe
<pb facs="tcp:2352:5"/>is so: neither all of the same schoole, Vniuersity, and colledge, be popish, because some one proueth to bee a papist. But the obiection of the thirde question pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth me worse then both the rest. Say it bee a matter conuenient that these motiues should be surprised be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they go any further; and the action as fit for me as another:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> yet how can I without the hand of presump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion present so small a worke to so great a personage?</p>
            <p>I confesse (most noble Earle) that I am at a losse, and know not herein what to answere: Onely that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable disposition, which I haue alwaies obserued in your Lordship, to receiue as your guests all that in the way of vertue and truth trauell towardes their iournies end of true happinesse, hath caused me an vnknowne traueller to make thus bold with your Honor: which boldenesse of loue, rather then loue of boldenesse, if at this time it may bee accepted without offence, I will passe my word for it, it shal neuer hereafter attempt the like, without further warrant of welcome from your Lordship. You fauored <hi>Alablaster</hi> whiles alablaster without spot: O let the same goodnesse in fauour de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scend vnto him that hateth his spots, but loueth him. The mother of vs both, the Vniuersity, once dignified, I had almost said deified with your presence, hath com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mitted her selfe vnto your patronage: maruaile not therefore (Right Honorable) though we her sons run together with our mother vnder the safegarde of your wings. The father of all, euen the God of mercy, blesse your Lordship and honorable familie vnto the worlds ende.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your honours euer most humblie deuoted, <hi>IOHN RACSTER.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:2352:5"/>
            <head>Ad Academicos &amp; suos salutem <hi>Longam, Epistolam breuem, mittit.</hi> I.R.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>LVdunt quidam, qui nos ludos faciunt, male feriati ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines: Academiam in delphinum mutatam, in motu tantum quietem capere.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertull. de virg. vel.</note>
               <hi>Nae tu (motor) magnum ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lae rei aedificans ad perniciē exemplum praebuisti, quod ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teres scandalum dixerunt. Nostis vero vos (doctissimi viri) quod vt nec in acie nec in vita, multo minùs in fide licebit, iniussu summi imperatoris stationem relinquere. Verumtamen sicut in humano ita &amp; ciuili corpore, &amp; morbi sunt &amp; remedia ijs adhibenda: Cumque tota quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rumcū{que} remediorum vis, adeo{que} medicina omnis duobus hisce consumatur: restitutione amissi, &amp; expulsione su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perflui: vestrum erit (Academici) si quid in Academia de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perditum sit restaurare, si quid supersit adhuc amoliri. Valete optimi optimè.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_the_reader">
            <head>Ad lectorem Epigramma Authoris.</head>
            <head type="sub">Pro captu lectoris habent sua fata libelli.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>IF <hi>Lippus</hi> read my bookes, they bleare-eyde be:</l>
               <l>If <hi>Linx,</hi> all spots, such eiesight haue those beasts.</l>
               <l>One sees too much, another cannot see;</l>
               <l>Mens tasts of wits, be diuerse, as of feasts.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:2352:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2352:6"/>
            <head>THE FIRST MOTIVE.</head>
            <div type="motive">
               <q>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the moyst and vnstable bodies because they are vnbounded in themselues, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer cease from motion vntill they bee stayed in some other body which hath stay in it selfe: so the vnderstanding, vnquiet by nature, passeth through all formes of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions vntill he resolue his assent vpon some principle that standeth onely vpon his owne ground.</hi>
               </q>
               <div type="remove">
                  <head>The remoue.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He rise of this first motiue (whiche see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to me banked vpon his similitude) expresly setteth out,
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> (though much I thinke against his will) the true causes not onely of this, but also of all the rest of his motiues: which be (as here you may see) an vnstable body, an vnderstanding vnquiet, nature without grace, and opinion voide of grounde. For as for that principle of Romish exposition of the scripture, which onely, (as he saith) standeth vpon his owne
<pb facs="tcp:2352:7"/>grounde, their two balifes, <hi>Corruptor stilus,</hi> a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt stile, and <hi>Adulter sensus,</hi> an adulterous sence, haue both morgaged and forfeited many yeares agoe; as I doe not doubte, but I shall easely make knowne by plaine euidence when I come to that pointe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="motive">
               <head>The motiue.</head>
               <q>
                  <hi>THerefore when the question of truth in contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersie of Faith is turned too and froe, in the thronge of so many particular quarrelles, it is best to go aside, and single out the two grand originals, and foundations from the which all the other factions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rise, that by taking the iust estimate of the strength of either, our iudgement may leane to the stronger part.</hi>
               </q>
               <div type="remove">
                  <head>The remoue.</head>
                  <p>THis counsell though it beare the face of good regarde; yet hath it the hart of rash attempte. Truth may bee tried, but faith must not be prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked. For the triall of truth maketh it perfect: but the doubting in faith, taketh away the strength of faith. And therefore when there is question of truth, it is good to be circumspecte; &amp; when there is controuersie of faith, it is best to bee constante. What rashnesse then is it in a matter of faith to go aside, wherby both faith and the truth be forsaken? Take the one of these without the other (I meane) the former without the latter, and I do not greatly
<pb facs="tcp:2352:7"/>mislike the counsell. Where truth is to be tryed by it selfe without any preiudice to faith in any question onely of truth, without controuersie of faith, it is best to goe aside, and to single out the maine points &amp; cheefe ground worke of the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion, that the naked truth may bee knowne, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out al colour of deceit. But if thou makest any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersy of faith; whilst thou doubtest of faith, thou hast no faith: And then commeth the aduersary and spying thee naked, and disarmed of the shield of faith striketh thee home on the heade, either with some dangerous errour, or damnable heresie. He that in skirmish knoweth not on which side to hold his shield, whilest he is yet a debating which side is best, he is sodainely stroken with the darte, and so he loseth his life; so likewise is it in the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall warfare, hee that maketh controuersie how to holde the shield of faith, whilest hee yet doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, the deuill letteth flie one of his fiery dartes, wherewith he is stroken to the harte; and so he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth his soule. It is not good to bee so busie vpon euery occasion with our eyes, least we put them out at the last: the eye of the soule is faith, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not good euer and anone to trouble it with controuersies, least we cleane put it out in the end. Wherefore my iudgement is cleane contrary to this of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> moter: What controuersies soeuer arise, it is best for vs to keep in the way of faith, not star<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting aside like a broken bowe, (as saith the Psalme) Nor stepping aside as our first parentes did, when they had eaten the forbidden fruite, whose facte
<pb facs="tcp:2352:8"/>we iustifie, when we, in matters of faith, goe aside, hyding our selues thereby from the face and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence of God. But it is our best, to doe the best we can to preuent al doubting. And if that cannot be, but wee must needes, as men, doubte, yet not to make factions of doubts, singling out (as cheefe champions of despaire, the cheefest doubts, that wee may bee singular in our infirmities. But when any controuersie of faith, which is doubte, doth arise, our practise must bee prayer, Lord I beleeue, helpe my vnbeleefe, and our comfort must bee the crosse of Christ: Not running to any rules of reason, which is to shallow to reach, much lesse to rule faith. And therefore as one faith of the lawe, so say I of faith. <hi>Fide semel data ex ea non de ea est disputandum.</hi> Hast thou faith? then from thence dispute what is reason, not from reason di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spute what is faith.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="motive">
               <head>The motiue.</head>
               <q>
                  <hi>AL particular controuersies in themselues stand vpon their yea and nay, but vnto vs require proofe; which proofe is linked by reason, which reason is cheefly grounded vpon scripture, which scripture is authorised not in the letter, but in the sence, because it is doubtfull in the variety of apprehensions; some leading, others drawing, many writhing their text to their seuerall factions: The question is at last remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from the text to the interpretor, from the scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, vnto the men. So that a mind studious of truth,
<pb facs="tcp:2352:8"/>is now come to his last care to determine of the worth, merit, &amp; authoritie of those that are the expositours.</hi>
               </q>
               <div type="remove">
                  <head>The remoue.</head>
                  <p>HEre the Moter eyther shooteth aboue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passe or sure I spie not his arrow. What lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicke I pray you call you this? All particular con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersies in themselues: I had alwaies thought that in the thinges themselues there is no contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersie, neither yet in the propositions themselues is there any probabilitie. But euery proposition in it selfe is eyther simply true, or simply false; but vnto vs who like night-rauens behold the light of the truth, things be made controuersies, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions become probable; not because they are so in themselues, but because we thinke them so: neither by reason that their causes bee doubtfull; but because we doubt of their causes, this causeth both yea and nay in the same matter, and this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth proofe on both sides.</p>
                  <p>Without this there is no controuersie, neither needeth there any proofe without this. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I could easely perswade my selfe though I knewe no more by him, the penner hereof, to be a papist, in that, in regard of his prentisage in pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, hee may not presume to workes of superero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, hee acquainteth himselfe in the meane time with wordes of the like qualitie. The like absurditie followeth in the next wordes where hee saith that poofe is lincked by reason: For if
<pb facs="tcp:2352:9"/>proofe be that, which the Philosopher in his Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torickes calleth <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, then is it the linke of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reasons, and is indeede in the true nature there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of nothing else, but the very reason of that whose proofe it is: and so consequently where hee saith that proofe is linked by reason, the wordes sound as if he had said: reason is linked by reason. But the reason that he thus linked reason, was to make a gradation or ladder, that he might at last clime to the authoritie of the bishoppe of Rome, which is the sphere that giueth motion to al his motiues.</p>
                  <p>But let vs come to the pitch of his purpose; which proofe saith hee is linked by reason: which reason is cheefly grounded vpon the scripture: which scripture is authorized not in the letter, but in the sence: here is the toppe of his ladder or cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>max: and on the toppe of this ladder hee placeth his Romish, falsely called catholicke, expositours.</p>
                  <p>Whome I doubt not with lesse adoe, in the sequell of this tractate to displace. In the meane time let vs consider his cunning in making his lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. The scripture is authorized not in the letter but in the sence. Beholde his boldnes; saint <hi>Paule</hi> in the second chapter to the Rom. and in the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond epistle and third chapter to the Corin. spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth otherwise; For hee maketh the opposition betweene the letter and the spirit: but our aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary is wiser then the apostle, and he maketh the opposition between the letter and the sense; lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing out in greate wisdome the spirit, because he knewe it would marre all their markets; as being
<pb facs="tcp:2352:9"/>that which the church of Rome, of all other chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, medleth least with. Neither, I am afraid, doth the spirit loue to communicate much with them. But howsoeuer he forgetteth himselfe, wee must challenge vnto the spirit his vpper place and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie: which is, to authorize the worde of God. In the worde of man bee <hi>Sensus humani,</hi> humane sence that giueth credit vnto it: but in the worde of God, there is <hi>Spiritus Dei,</hi> the spirite of God that authorizeth it. And looke what sence is to the word of man, the same is the spirit to the worde of God. And surely they make but base account of the worde of God that censure it in the sense: put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting no difference betweene the worde of God, and the worde of man; naye it seemeth they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre the worde of man before the worde of God, when they place the whole authoritie thereof in the sence, and the sence it selfe and credit thereof in the expositours, which be indeed the buts that the moter shooteth at in this place. For thus hee concludeth. The question at last is remoued from the text to the interpretour, from the scripture vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to men. Very badly, beleeue me is it remoued, and it is long of themselues. For were it that they did attribute all to the spirit as we do, and not insteade of the Apostle his spirite, bring in their sence, that they themselues might haue some authoritie ouer the worde of God, because they thinke they haue some sense: there needed no remoue from text to interpretour, from the scripture vnto men. But the same spirit that writeth the scripture shoulde
<pb facs="tcp:2352:10"/>iudge of the scripture: and where y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> iudge was not to be found, that not to bee accounted scripture. Which may very well be done &amp; easely be found out by conference of places: in that the spirite is one and the same in all places, alwaies alike, like it selfe alwaies, &amp; neuer differing in any point from it selfe. And therfore where there is any difference in substance of doctrine, there must needes bee a differing spirite, whereby that place that thus dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth from some one, or many places of the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicall scripture, and knowne word of God: may iustly be suspected to be the worde of man. And as for the diuersitie of exposition, according to the varietie of factions in religion, (which the moter iustly taxeth, with leading, drawing, and writhing the worde of God to serue their owne turne) it is not the outward shewe, merit or worth of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positours, but the inward working of the spirite of God, that doth resolue the mind studious of the truth, being first sanctified by praier and prepared by humility. For what saith our sauior Christ spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the same spirit in the gospel? He shal leade you into all truth. And therefore he onely is the competent iudge: neither ought we to rely vpon any mans iudgement, besides this: because euery man will bring somthing of his owne, howsoeuer, it may be he is instructed in some pointes by this spirite. The heathen Philosopher knew this, that mans iudgment is tempered with the hand of his affection: and therefore hee especially commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth those lawes, that leaue least to the will, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2352:10"/>discretion of the iudge. And so likewise as that lawe, so is that religion most sound, that referreth al to the written word of God; leauing least in the power and hand of mans iudgment: wherefore that I may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this point, and aunswere him in all pointes, I will make a truer gradation, I hope, then hee hath done.</p>
                  <p>All controuersies in the world stand vpon their yea &amp; nay, but vnto vs require proofe, which proofe is limited by faith, which faith is grounded wholy vpon the scripture, which scripture is authorized not in the letter but in the spirit.</p>
                  <p>So that a mind studious of the truth is now to come to his last labour, to begge at the hands of his heauenly Father, that he would giue him such a por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his spirite, that his spirite may expounde the scripture, that the scripture may confirme faith, that faith may rectifie reason, that reason may reforme our iudgments in all controuersies whatsoeuer, that we neuer either mistake errour, or mislike the truth. <hi>Det Deus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="motive">
               <head>The motiue.</head>
               <q>
                  <hi>THe catholick part for the strength of their interpre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tation, alledge the iudgement of the Church, the definition of councels, the consent of Fathers, the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of churches, the practise of al ages, and the rule of Apostolicall tradition, left by succession as the light thorough the heauens.</hi>
               </q>
               <div type="remove">
                  <pb facs="tcp:2352:11"/>
                  <head>The remoue.</head>
                  <p>HAuing, as he thought, brought the matter to a good passe, by bringing all cōtrouersies, proofs, reasons, yea and the scripture it selfe vnder the tuiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the expositours: he laboureth in this place all that he may, to shew the Romish (whom he vainly calleth catholick) part, to be the onely lawfull heires of sound interpretation; which shew of his is brauely set out with six pagents. First, as of most worth, com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meth in on the expositors side, the iudgment of the church: in the second place marcheth the definition of councels: thirdly to colour the matter better, the consent of fathers: fourthly y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> harmony of churches: fiftly the practise of all ages; and lastly the rule of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postolicall tradition. Surely a braue shewe: but you must vnderstand, that when he hath all said, he hath al done: for he bringeth no proofe for any thing that he saith: and therefore we will do him that fauour to set downe some proofes for him.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="1" type="pageant">
                  <head>The first pagent.</head>
                  <p>THat which is allowed by the church of Rome, is approued in the iudgment of the church, (for he meaneth nothing by the church but the church of Rome, which is the church <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the eminent church) but the romish exposition is allowed by the church of Rome: therefore the Romish exposition is approued in the iudgment of the church. What though the heretickes Iewell, Whitakers, Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noldes,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2352:11"/>Stephanus,
<note place="margin">Vir illa Steph.</note> and Fox do shew y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Pope Ioane was an whore, pope Hildebrand a coniurer, &amp; Hono<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rius condemned for an heriticke: Though the head of the church be an heretick, yet the church cannot erre. What though Thomas be against Scotus, and Scotus against Thomas, Soto bee on neyther side, Bellarmine on all sides, and Caietaine against all? Though euery member of the church be out of the way, yet the church it selfe cannot step aside. Wee catholickes cary our church in our bosome. For mine owne parte, I neither hould what Thomas houldeth, nor what Scotus, neither hould I with So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, Caietane, Bellarmine, or any one or other papist whatsoeuer: but what the church holdeth that hold I: If the question be what the church holdeth, I am as able to determin of it as another. This is no meere fiction, but the true substance of this secte, which I my selfe haue heard from some of their mouths that think themselues no cast-away catholickes, euen frō the very man y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> standeth so stifly in this place vpon y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> iudgment of the church, if I be not much deceiued.</p>
                  <div type="appendix">
                     <head>The Apendix.</head>
                     <p>BVt if by the iudgment of the church he meaneth the true church; then this is the censure thereof betweene the Apostles &amp; their succeeding interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours. The Apostles were the indoubted authentical scribes of the holy Ghost; and therfore their writings are no otherwise to be accounted of, but as the infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible oracles of God. But their succeeders, and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretours haue no other commission but to teach that which is sealed and deliuered vnto vs in holy
<pb facs="tcp:2352:12"/>writ: and thereupon the church concludeth this, as a maxime or axiome not to be denied: That no suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeder or interpretor may forge, or coyne any newe doctrine or opinion, but shall cleaue simply to that doctrine, vnto which God hath brought all without exception to subiection: which who dare say the Romish expositours do not?</p>
                     <p>When they picke purgatory out of Peters purse, and Peter pence out of others purses: make that a praier, which the angell maketh a salutation: cal that canonical, which is contrary in some points to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicall scripture: euery Pope after the minte was once vp, adding some new deuise of his owne, which <hi>Prauá solertiá,</hi> by the euill wittinesse of some of their interpretours must needes find countenance in the word of God. Which being once made as a fit shoo for the popes foote, yet seeming too litle vnder the title of the writer, it is set vpon the last of the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of that church to make it seeme greater.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="pageant">
                  <head>The second pageant and the discouery thereof.</head>
                  <p>THe decree of a councell is the acte of Christ: where two or three are gathered togither in my name, there am I in the midest of them. <hi>Mat. 18.20.</hi> But the Popish interpretours haue the decrees of councels, as of the second Nicene, &amp; second Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sine, and such like, for their warrant: and therefore their exposition must needes bee good, as flowing from the fountaine of goodnesse, God himselfe. I as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure you a braue pagent but yet too full of colours, take some of the colours away, and you shall see the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:2352:12"/>truth. The decree of a councel that is squared accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Christ his rule: that is, <hi>in nomine meo,</hi> gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red togither and working in the name of Christ, and for the glory of Christ, is directed by Christ.</p>
                  <p>But not all councels whatsoeuer. Not Achab his councell of fowre hundred men: for the president of that councell was Satan, a lyeng spirit in the mouth of all the prophets. Not the councell of the high priestes and pharisies, which in outward shewe car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried the same glosse that the popish councels doe. For this councell was held against Christ: but those councels only which containe nothing but the true, pure, and naturall interpretation of the scripture: which the holy fathers in a spirituall wisedome, to breake the power of the enimies of the church, fitted vnto their owne times. Such were those councels of olde, the first Nicene Synod, the councell of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantinople, the first Ephesine &amp; Calcedon councel, and such like. And not those latter councels, wherin the wolues killed the lambes, for troubling the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which they themselues had corrupted. The first and the best be for vs, and the last and the worst bee for them; which to let goe many other) this one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance will manifest vnto vs. Aboue nine hundred yeares agoe the Synode of Constantinople decreed images placed in churches to be ouerthrowne, and broken downe; this is for vs: A little after that, the councel of Nicene, decreede to restore them againe, and this is for them: which both Augustine and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piphanius condemne as the next part to Idolatrie: which paire of councels may be paraleled by two o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; we allow of the councell of Calcedon, wherin
<pb facs="tcp:2352:13"/>Eutiches his heresie was condemned. They com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended the second Ephesine councel wherin it was confirmed. Now let them brag of their councels who can shew most good cōming from them. The badges of their councels be idolatry and heresie: but those councels that stand for vs can be taxed with no impietie: And yet forsooth hee braueth vs with the definition of councels: which if he meane the good and generall councels, then is it but a florish, neither dareth he be tried by them: but if he meane the bad and the prouinciall Synodes, then harpeth he all vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on one string, and saith no more then before he said. For they make those councels to be the very image and liuely paterne of the church. And what then I pray you can the definition of councels be else, but the iudgement of the church according to his mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning? Neither is it greatly materiall what those Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nodes do define, for they are nothing else, but the Pope his voice which hee ruleth high or lowe at his pleasure: neither is there any true born Christian that will take his othe, much lesse build his faith vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the bare worde of the Pope, without warrant from the worde of God.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="pageant">
                  <head>The third pagent with the disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery thereof.</head>
                  <p>THe consent of the fathers giue great credit vnto the writinges of any man, in that they cary both the countenance of Antiquity &amp; the maintenance of verity.</p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:2352:13"/>
                  <p>But the Romish impostors, expositours I should say, haue the consent of the fathers: as father Peter, aliás Lombard, father Thomas, aliás Aquine, father Robert, aliás Bellarmine, and such like. And therfore who can deny but their writings bee orthodoxall. The truth is, there is no man can deny but that they haue a whole calender of these sainctes; matching the superstitious Gods of their Heathenish forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, with their owne Idolatrous sainctes. But which of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> fathers indeed did euer follow their fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, or fancy their followers? Where did Ambrose giue his consent that those wordes of our Sauiour Christ: <hi>Tues Petrus:</hi> thou art Peter, &amp;c. to bee ment of Peters chaire at Rome, and of the bishop that sit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vpon that chaire, and of the dignity and supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riority of that bishop;
<note place="margin">The coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell at A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quilaia.</note> when hee himselfe in an vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersall councell held in Italy did sit downe first him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe without any mention or regarde of the bishop of Rome or of his chaire?
<note place="margin">Li 3. Epist. 76. Lib. 4. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pist. ad Eulol.</note> Where doth saint Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory fancy the followers of that folly? when hee himselfe with might and maine exclameth in many places against the name, and title of an vniuersall bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop? calling it a prophane nay a sacrilegious name, the forerunner of Antichrist, and the inuention of the diuell, who despising the society and felowship of Angels, would needes be singular, though it were but in absurditie.</p>
                  <p>Whose apes they are who are apt to despise others in the nouelty &amp; affectation of singularity. Let him shew if he can where Augustine, Chrysostom, Basil, Nazianzene, Cyprian, Iustin Martyr, Athana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sius, Epiphanius, Tertullian, or any of the Fathers
<pb facs="tcp:2352:14"/>fauored any of their interpretations, as touching the reall presence in the Lords supper. The inuocation of Saints, praier for the dead, or any such trumpery: and then I will hold their religion to be, <hi>Satis auto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratam consensus patrocinio.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="pageant">
                  <head>The fourth Pagent, <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of Churches.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe harmony of Churches consorting in false religion, is the conspiracy of theeues robbing God of his honour.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="pageant">
                  <head>The fift Pagent discouered.</head>
                  <p>THe practise of all ages hath beene to peruert the truth, &amp; to hinder the gospell by false interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. In our Sauiour Christ his time satan himselfe wrested this writ to his own sense.</p>
                  <p>In the Apostles times, among the Epistles of <hi>Paul</hi> some things are harde to be vnderstood, which they that are vnlearned and vnstable, peruert as they doe also other scriptures, vnto their owne destruction, saith saint <hi>Peter. 2</hi> of <hi>Peter 3.16.</hi> Not long after in the primitiue church <hi>Ebion</hi> and <hi>Cerinthus</hi> hereticks of that time did the like: after them <hi>Donatus, Noua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, Arius</hi> and the rest: and nowe at this time, and a long time since the papists haue plaied their parts in apish, childish and ridiculous interpretations, as wel practised as any of the rest. And thus he may proue his pagent, that it hath beene the practise of all ages to worke in the mystery of iniquity, as wel as theirs; as the Apostle <hi>Paule</hi> witnesseth: thus they may plead
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:2352:14"/>their custome, and to say the truth wee cannot deny it them; for they haue as much to shew for it as any, and can prescribe as long time as any out of the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of man, which some say, is good in lawe. But yet I would not haue them brag too much of their custome, for a custome maketh a good thing neuer better, but it maketh a bad thing much the worse: &amp; this is the cause why the latter is still the worser age. And bicause he speaketh of al ages, I will deuide the ages of the world into three, which is the leaste all that may be: not following the diuision of Rabby E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lias in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> fatall period of euery two thousand yeares,
<note place="margin">Duo millia ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, duo millia lex, duo millia euangelium.</note> making a change, and the end at the last: but accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our best diuines, numbring by persons, not diuiding by numbers the three ages of the worlde. From Adam to Moises is accounted the first age of the worlde; from Moyses to Christ the second age of the worlde; and from Christ vnto the end of the worlde the last. From Adam to Moises, and from Moyses vnto Christ is set downe in holy writte. Let vs now search what hath beene the practise in this last age of the world of all ages of men.</p>
                  <p>For euery age of the world containeth many ages of men. First therefore (as I tolde you) euen in the Apostles times, the mystery of iniquitie begon to be put in practise: for euen then Ebion and Cerinthus, as I tolde you, Simon Magus, Basilides, and Nicolas begon to set abroach their damnable heresies. After the Apostles ages there arose yet more malitious &amp; wicked men then these, as Marcion, Manes, Marcus Magius, Valentius and many others. But in this our age this practise groweth euery day worse &amp; worse:
<pb facs="tcp:2352:15"/>For now the deuill himselfe, who was bound in the bottomlesse pit for a thousand yeares after Christ: <hi>Reuela. 20.3.</hi> the time of his imprisonment being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pired, is now let loose and come into the world. And as his kingdome decreaseth by the hastening of the comming of Christ; so his malice increaseth, and he doth more vex and trouble the church: which cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of his that wee may the better discouer, it wil not be amisse to set downe vnto you fiue alterations of church states in this last age of the world. The first, (that you may know how euill stroue still to preuent good in the birthright of this worlde) was the time of suffering or persecution of the church, contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the martyrdom of the saints in the ten persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which continued from the Apostles three hundreth yeres. And then came in the florishing time of the church, which containeth other 300. yeers. Then thirdly followed the declining, or back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sliding time of the church, which comprehendeth other 300. yeares euen vntill the loosing of Sathan, which was about the thousand yeare after Christ. Fourthly followeth the time of Antichrist, or the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solation of the church, wherin the puritie of doctrin, and sincerity of life, was almost clean extinguished, especially in the daies of Gregory the seuenth called Hildebrand, and Innocentius the third amongst the prelates and heades of the church: the time wherin Antichrist had thus his ful swinge, was for the space of foure hundred yeares: From Pope Boniface the thirde, to the time of Wicklife and Iohn Husse. Fiftly the reformation, and purging of the church of God: which reformation beeing hid with the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2352:15"/>prophets in the time of Elias in caues of Christian mens hearts, by the space of fower hundred yeares, about some three hundred yeares since ventred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad into the world, was viewed, liked, &amp; allowed of all the louers of the truth. Now then if you would know the birth of popery: it was a breeding a long time in proud and ambitious minds: but the full age from the birth thereof is seuen hundred yeares or therabouts, &amp; not 1500. yeares as the moter would haue it. For before that time there was no Pope, no popish doctrine nor discipline: but the same forme of doctrine and discipline, which was faine to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered by reformation; and thereupon our religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is called and accounted a reformation, which is nothing else but a recouery of the former forme. Which forme of Religion was taught by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles, sealed with the bloud of saints in the time of persecution, and practised in the florishing time of the church, long before the world euer heard of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, but onely in the mystery of Antichrist.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="pageant">
                  <head>The sixt pagent Aposto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall tradition.</head>
                  <p>THe church of Rome maketh two seruices of the truth: there be <hi>scriptae,</hi> written truthes, and they bee in the scripture: there bee <hi>non scriptae,</hi> vnwritten truthes, and they be their traditions, to speake of all traditions would run vs all out of breath. The chiefe of all is apostolicall tradition, the rule wherof is sure some vertue left by Peter in the Popes chaire: which remaineth yet vnworne out (though deliuered from
<pb facs="tcp:2352:16"/>hand to hand by euery Pope) vnto his succeeder. By the benefit of which vertue the Pope granteth war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the truth, as iustices do with vs of the peace. By which warrants as the naturall light in the firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the heighest heauen, passeth thorough the sphere of fixed stars, and the seuen spheres of the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, and so cōmeth vnto vs: So the light of the truth issueth from the pope, as the <hi>primum mobile,</hi> vnto the fixed seats, spheres, I should say, of Cardinals and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops, and from them vnto the wandring planets of their writers and interpretors. And this I take the Moter meaneth by the rule of apostolicall tradition, left by succession as the light through the heauens.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="motive">
               <head>The motiue.</head>
               <q>
                  <hi>THe Protestants bring forth the seuerall founders of their sects,</hi> Luther, Caluin, Melācthon, <hi>&amp; others of that straine, whose exposition they cleaue vnto.</hi>
               </q>
               <div type="remove">
                  <head>The remooue.</head>
                  <p>THe Protestants are greatly beholding vnto the Moter, for mustering of their men without their charges: but yet he must aske pardon of their grand captaine Iesus Christ, whom no doubt he hath grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uously offended, for making those men founders of the Protestantes, who were but his vnder officers, and at the best but his lieutenants; and therefore hee hath surely done Christ great iniury in taking his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice from him: for he only is our founder, and the rest be but master builders. And yet surely in my opiniō,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2352:16"/>it behooueth vs and the whole church to giue God infinite thanks, for those singular instruments wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by his truth is conuaied vnto vs. Neither see I anie thing in the zealous spirit of <hi>Luther,</hi> nor in the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned writings of <hi>Caluin,</hi> nor in the sincere life &amp; doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of <hi>Melancthon,</hi> which the aduersary may iustly despise. And yet doe wee not so receiue these men for our guides, that wee make them our gods: beleeuing them presently whatsoeuer they say, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they say it, and cannot say amisse, though they erre lesse then the pope doth: they haue not this cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit with vs.</p>
                  <p>But whatsoeuer they prooue by manifest demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stration out of the word, that am I bolde to beleeue. For then heare I not <hi>Luther, Caluin,</hi> &amp; <hi>Melancthon</hi> speake vnto me: but the spirit of God by the mouth of <hi>Luther, Caluin</hi> and <hi>Melancthon,</hi> for they be but the instruments of that spirit. Thus hauing bestowed his liberality vpon the church of Rome in giuing them more then they know euer how to deserue: and play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the niggard with the church of God in denying them that which of duty they ought to haue had; he commeth at last to compare his owne conceipts to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, for as for the thinges he talketh of, hee spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of either, as though he knew neither.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="motive">
               <head>The motiue.</head>
               <q>
                  <hi>LAy this in the ballance &amp; waigh together the spouse of Christ, with</hi> Luther, Caluin, Melancthon, <hi>oecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menical coūcels, with priuate opinions. The reuerent &amp; learned fathers with</hi> Arius, Aetius Vigilantius: <hi>men
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2352:17"/>alwaies in their time burned for heretickes. The har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of Churches with the iarring of conuenticles, of them that are in as great brawle with themselues as with the catholickes. The vniforme practise of 1500. yeares with the often change of others. The tradition of the Apostles with the dregs of hereticks.</hi>
               </q>
               <div type="remove">
                  <head>The remooue.</head>
                  <p>IF at any time heretofore, much more at this time the old prouerbe is verified: <hi>Comparisons be odious.</hi> For surely this is a most odious and detestable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parison: not so much in the comparison it selfe, (though that also bee a shamefull thing to compare Christ with antichrist, the church of God with the church of Rome, a modest matrone with a shameles whore) as in the priuiledged lies, and authorised slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders that he bringeth. I call them priuiledged lyes, in that it seemeth the Pope hath made a priuiledge for any of his to lye on his behalfe: and againe autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rised slanders, for that by the same authority there is commission granted to slander vs at their pleasure: with what face can he call that the spouse of Christ, that runneth a whoring after euery saint? what shew of oecumenicall councels, whose center is the Pope and circumference his pompe? what Fathers can he shewe, but onely the children of the father of false<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoode? what harmony call you that, where al is out of tune? what vniforme practise, what Apostolicall tradition, where the Apostle is the stale to practise the Popes trade? On the otherside, forsooth wee haue no lectorer but <hi>Luther,</hi> no doctor but <hi>Caluin,</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:2352:17"/>no maister but <hi>Melancthon.</hi> Our common conclusi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons be priuate opinions, our consent is iarring, our constancy is change, our doctrine is dregs.</p>
                  <p>If <hi>Luther, Caluin,</hi> and <hi>Melancthon,</hi> be our onelie masters, then who taught <hi>Wicklife</hi> &amp; <hi>Iohn Husse,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their time? Nay, who taught the Christians in the primitiue Church? for they differ not at all from them: the only difference is between you and them, by denying you all those pointes, which haue beene knowne both by the time, the occasion, and person; when, vpon what occasion, and by whom they haue been brought in since the primatiue church. If com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon be priuate, and conclusions opinions; if consent be iarring, &amp; constancy change; if councels be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenticles and doctrine dregs: then truth is falshood, and good is bad. For the further proofe of euery one of these points, I will expect the returne of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which wil, I knowe be, not without some pause: for at this time I know hee hath runne himselfe out of breath. Nowe let vs see his golden <hi>Epiphonema,</hi> which he vseth after this goodly manner in the next wordes.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="motive">
               <head>The motiue.</head>
               <q>
                  <hi>NOwe let any man (though ouerballanced by affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) consider with himselfe whether of these should be beleeued in expounding the scriptures, and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently in the truth of the controuersies which relyeth vpon the sense.</hi>
               </q>
               <div type="remove">
                  <pb facs="tcp:2352:18"/>
                  <head>The remoue</head>
                  <p>AS he that goeth a coursing when he hath found his game letteth slip with this incouragement, Now: So the nimble moter, coursing in his kinde, thinking belike his game to bee vp, vseth the same worde of incouragement, Now: but as if the bussard be blind, and in steed of an hare letteth slip at a brake bush, his wordes be but wind, and his course is but lost. So fareth it with the moter blinded in his affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in steade of feare and flying; finding constancy and perseuerance shall know his wordes to bee but wind, and his course to be lost.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <head>THE SECOND MOTIVE.</head>
            <div type="motive">
               <q>
                  <hi>THE mysteries of religion doe so far exceede the narrowe straites of our vnderstanding, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they cannot be comprehended by reason: God hath therefore appointed Faith to entertaine them, which faith is built vpon diuine and vnfallible authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, the minde yeelding obedience in steade of discourse, and receiuing indifferently the truth of doctrine, vpon the credit and affiance of the teacher.</hi>
               </q>
               <div type="remove">
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:2352:18"/>
                  <head>The remoue.</head>
                  <p>A Good beginning maketh a good ende: that is true, where a good workeman in a good intent not hindered otherwise, taketh the matter in hand. But where either the workeman is hindered in his proceedinges, or meaneth no true dealing, or is not his crafts maister; there the beginning may be indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent, the middle worse, and the ende worst of all. What euer the matter be, the beginning of this mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue is not to be misliked, the middle not to be liked, and the ende not to bee, but misliked: whether his art was not good, or his faith not good, or his lucke not good, that know I not. But sure I thinke his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose was to frame this motiue according to that forme of syllogisme, which is the worst of the foure, called by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Philosopher <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, making a the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ologicall proposition to lead an hereticall conclusi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: by little and little incroching with falseshoode vpon the truth, as the night stealeth vppon the day. And therfore the best way to try his truth, is to trace him in the tracte of his own tractate.</p>
                  <p>The mysteries of religion are out of the reach of reason: which is the reason that God hath giuen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his a larger hande of faith to apprehende them. Which faith, laieth the foundation Christ, in the authoritie of diuine and infallible truth, by yeelding the minde beleeuing without doubt, and obedient without discourse. Hitherto as I thinke we go toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. But where further he saith: And receiuing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently the truth of doctrine, vpon the credit and
<pb facs="tcp:2352:19"/>affiance of the teacher. Here wee leaue him though he did beare vs company all the way before, that he might at the least bring vs vnto this.
<note place="margin">Actes. 28.11</note> The men of Berea though they had as good a teacher as euer came to Rome, yet are they commended as more noble men, then the men of Thessalonica in that they had not such confidence in their teachers, but that they would search the scriptures daily, whether those things were so. Here was the credite that they gaue vnto their teachers which also is cōmended, to examin his word by the word of God: placing their chiefe affiance, not in the minister, but in the author of the word of God. For whosoeuer wil belieue al tea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chers shall be of all religions: but he only shall be of the true religion that relyeth wholy vpon the worde of God: and therefore this only, saith <hi>S. Hillary,</hi> is the rule of faith. <hi>Dicit Dominus, dicit Apostolus,</hi> the Lord saith it, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Apostle saith it; which is a thousand times of more waight and worth, then <hi>Dicit papa, dicit con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilium,</hi> the Pope saith it, the councell saith it, which is their rule of faith. Wherefore, that we may ioyne issues with the aduersary, wee will come to the next point.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="motive">
               <head>The motiue.</head>
               <q>
                  <hi>THerefore that religion which doth not stay the as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent of the scholler, and irrefragable authority in al matters of faith, hath neither merit of beliefe in it selfe nor others.</hi>
               </q>
               <div type="remove">
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:2352:19"/>
                  <head>The remooue.</head>
                  <p>YOu wil get much by this match: the authority that staieth our faith stoppeth all controuersies in faith,
<note place="margin">Gardiner at his death.</note> and winneth the absolute assent of the schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers vnto it, is so irrefragable, that the hardiest on your side haue beene constrained in the end to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, and to confesse the same; though the politicke practise of their aspiring mindes made other shew in their life time; which policy against conscience pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaileth likewise with the Moter in his discourse fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="motive">
               <head>The motiue.</head>
               <q>
                  <hi>BVt such is the discipline of the protestants, that they affoord their schollers no other but humane and mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table authority, whereby to beleeue the number and dignitie of the scriptures, with the sence and interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of them, in which consisteth the sum of al religiō.</hi>
               </q>
               <div type="remove">
                  <head>The remooue.</head>
                  <p>BVt here the moter speaketh clean against his own conscience. For he cannot bee ignorant that wee approoue of the number and dignity of scriptures, with the sense and interpretation, according to the testimony of the spirit, the analogy of faith, and the correspondency or consanguinity of doctrine of those that be canonicall, with the difference and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersity of the others. First the testimony of the spirit teacheth to knowe the number, and to beleeue the
<pb facs="tcp:2352:20"/>dignity of the scriptures. First in that the spirit of God registreth all those as canonicall, which either Christ or his disciples do auouch as general proofes, or drawe any directe consequence, not meaning those particular proofes, which by oblique reference as the wrtings of heathen men are mentioned in the holy scriptures: and thus can I shew you by expresse places, al the bookes that our church holdeth cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical, and not any other, that I remember, auouched by the holy ghost as autentical proofe for any point. Secondly the testimony of Iesus is the spirit of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phesie, as saith the spirit of God in the 19. of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uela.</hi> 10. and therefore those bookes of holie writ, that either prophesie or beare witnesse of Iesus; they haue the testimony of the spirit that they are the word of God: which is one way to knowe both the number and the dignity of the scriptures. Againe; the Analogy; of faith is another way by which wee reckon, and make reckoning of scriptures. Those bookes of holy writ that teach Christ and nothing contray to the analogy of faith, those we make rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning of as canonicall; those that be otherwise we reiect as apocripha. And this analogy of faith is no mutable, but a most sufficiēt directiō to those y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> haue true faith. If therefore the Papists mislike this rule of analogy of faith, it is a doubt they do misdoubt they haue true faith. Thirdly, one scripture compared by another, doth shew which is scripture: the worde is like the words of Christ who spake with authority and not as the Pharisies. So is there in the worde of God, such an assurance and a maiesty which is not to be found in the word of man. I wil giue you a taste
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2352:20"/>of both kinds in the conclusion of two bookes. The last of <hi>Iohn</hi> the two last verses. This is the disciple that testifieth of these things, &amp; wrote these thinges, and we knowe his testimony to be true. Nowe there are also many other thinges which Iesus did, the which if they should be written euery one, I suppose the world could not containe the books that should be written. What an assurance is here? we know his testimony is true: what a maiesty? the world is too little for it. On the other side, reade the last of the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond of <hi>Machabees</hi> and the last verse saue one. If I haue don wel, &amp; as the story required, it is the thing that I desired; but if I haue spoken slenderly, it is that I could. What a weakenesse is here? hee knewe not whether he had done wel or no. If I haue done wel, &amp;c. and what a basenesse? It is all that I coulde. In like sort, if you compare other places of other books canonicall and apocripha, you shall finde that the word of God is all sincere <hi>sine ceramel,</hi> hony with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out waxe, truth without toies. But the word of man, say it hath a little hony, some truth, yet if you looke into it with a single eie you shall finde much waxe, many ridiculous toies of humane inuentions. And therefore the cōparison of scripture is a right touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stone of scripture. Wherefore if the testimony of the spirit, the analogy of faith, and the conformitie of the word of God bee constant and diuine: then is our beliefe warranted with more sufficient, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine authority, then that that dependeth vppon the church, and is pinned to the Pope his sleeue. For that may bee like our lawe; which is (as they say) so mutable, that that which hath bin lawe in one chiefe
<pb facs="tcp:2352:21"/>iustices time, is no lawe in anothers: So may that which hath beene scripture in one Popes time, bee no scripture in anothers; or that which hath beene none, may be when it pleaseth the Pope. And thus you see my reasons on our behalfe, nowe let vs see his reasons against vs.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="motive">
               <head>The motiue.</head>
               <q>
                  <hi>FOr they affirme the authoritie of the church and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistery, of whom their followers receiue both the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred scriptures and their expositours, be humane and such as may go aside into errour &amp; sometimes do. So that of necessitie whosoeuer standeth in the integritie of their opinion, eyther haue no faith at al, or else onely hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane and errant. For they that haue a possible impoten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of erring in one point of faith, what assurance can they make of distinction, that they do not erre in all.</hi>
               </q>
               <div type="remove">
                  <head>The remoue.</head>
                  <p>WEe say indeede that our ministers be men, and that all Christians, which be the church mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, be no Gods, though neerest in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> fauor of God. Wherfore considering our nature,
<note place="margin">Can. 1.4 Can. 5.2 Can. 5.3 Can. 5.6</note> we acknowledge with the spouse of Christ in the Canticles our owne blacknesse, drowsinesse, nakednesse, sloathfulnesse &amp; errour. But looke vnto the spouse of Christ: grace from him giueth vs, and the whole church of Christ, beauty, cloathing, watchfulnes and truth. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the case standeth thus: while the church loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vpon Christ, and harkneth vnto his voyce, she
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:2352:21"/>cannot erre; for in him is all truth, his worde is truth it selfe. But wee must know that, as there it is, the church somtime sleepeth, and her spouse standeth without knocking and calling vnto her. But because her cloathes bee off, she is loath to put them on a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: because her feet are washed she excuseth her selfe, for feare of defiling them in comming to let him in: Then putteth he in his hand, that is, sheweth his kindenesse and liberalitie vnto her, at the hole of the doore, that is, at that parte of the heart that lieth open to his grace: Then openeth she the doore, but then he is gone and past; because her harte was gone when he did speake: therefore is he gone when she openeth. I sought him but could not find him. Then wandereth the church and erreth, she is taken by the watch and hardly intreated vntil she find him again: and then she is safe and erreth not.</p>
                  <p>This then is the truth that the protestantes holde in this point. In any matter necessary vnto saluation the church cannot finally erre: but it is not long of her owne wisdome, but because renouncing all her own wisdom, she giueth herselfe, wholy to be taught by the spirit of God, according vnto his word to know and acknowledge her spouse. But yet some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times forgetting her selfe, in too much remenbring herselfe neglecteth her loue: by whose departure she may and doth erre in some matters. This the church of God holdeth: but it seemeth by the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> church of Rome holdeth the cleane contrary, in that he addeth immediatly the contrary practise of their church: when he saith.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="motive">
               <pb facs="tcp:2352:22"/>
               <head>The motiue.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>COntrary the Catholickes auouching the inflexible truth of the church as the voice of Christ, &amp; directi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of the spirit, doth stay the mindes of the faithful from doubt and wauering. But the other making an head from the body of the church are rightly punished, both with beleefe in errours and vnbeleefe in truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="remove">
                  <head>The remooue.</head>
                  <p>THis I take the moter meaneth by the inflexible truth of the church: That seeing the church is gouerned by the spirit of God, it may safely walke where it list without the worde; whither soeuer it goeth it cannot eyther speake or thinke any thing but the truth. And therfore if it determine any thing, eyther without or besides the word of God, it is no otherwise to be accounted, then a most certaine and vndoubted oracle of God. This therfore is the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betweene them and vs. They place the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of the church without the worde: but wee will haue it so knit, coupled, and tyed vnto the worde, that it cannot be separated or diuorced from it. For this is the discipline of a wel ordered, both house &amp; schoole, that the spouse, &amp; disciple of Christ should submit her selfe vnto the will and worde of her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band and maister: when as if she doth what shee list her selfe, without any commission from Christ, then is shee like those good huswiues that commaunde their husbandes our of doores. And if this bee their dealing, it is no maruaile though the church of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:2352:22"/>Rome holdeth so much of our Lady: for so some say, those houses do, where the wiues beare away y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers. I, but forfooth saith the Moter, this taketh away all doubt and wauering. It is true indeed, as in those hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses where the seruants seeke to please their mistris, not caring howe they displease their maister. But as those euill disposed seruants, for their too much loue to the one, are thought often times in the iudgement of the worlde, to play false with the other: So is it with those seruants of Christ, that had rather please the church then Christ, it cannot bee but both they, and their church be adulterous in the iudgement of the Lorde. Yea, but she hath commission from Christ, in that she h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th the direction of the spirit: <hi>Iohn. 14.20.</hi> The spirit w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ich I will send from my father, shall bring you into all t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uth. But you must vnderstand that this commissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is not without the limitation, of <hi>Quae dixi vobis,</hi> which told you: shall teach you all thinges, and bring all thiges into your remembrance which I told you. Yea, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t the decree of the church is the very voyce of Christ why then let her vse the wordes of Christ, and we will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eleeue her. For that voice only is directed by the sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>it of God, that speaketh the worde of God. W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ich case S. Chrysostome setteth downe clearelie were he saith. <hi>Multi Spiritum sanctum iactant: sed qui <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>opria loquūtur falsò illum praetendunt:</hi> Many do boast of the holy Ghost, but they doe but make a false pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of him, that speake of themselues. In the end of this Motiue, he chargeth vs for making a head from y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> body of the church: but we may more iustly chalenge thē for making two heads on the body of the church. For Christ will bee one head whether they will or no: And the Pope shall bee the other, whether Christ will
<pb facs="tcp:2352:23"/>or no, or else they will be no church, which I easily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue. But our beliefe is error, and our vnbeliefe truth. Poore soule, thy vnbeliefe in our beliefe, and thy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe of our vnbeliefe, is thine errour in truth, and the truth of thine error.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="part">
            <head>THE THIRD MOTIVE.</head>
            <div type="motive">
               <q>
                  <hi>THE infinite waies of errours drawe themselues in their originall into two heads, opinion and affection which (as two cankers) breed the one in the vnde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, the other in the will: for our iudgement is asi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est deceiued, by those things we esteeme truest, and or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination by what we loue best.</hi>
               </q>
               <div type="remove">
                  <head>The remoue</head>
                  <p>IT is a rule in Philosophy, that, <hi>nihilagit exti sphaerā actiuitatis sua,</hi> Nothing by nature can workwithout the circuit of his own shop or workehouse. The fishes cannot flie, as birdes in the ayre: neither can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e birds swim, as the fishes within the water. And there<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>re it was pretily said of a learned lawyer of this land v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> a noble warrier, when hee was as loude and lusty in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Star-chamber as he vsed to be in the field: Sir remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber your selfe, We are not now in your element: The like may I say vnto the Moter, striuing to bee as fine in philosophy as he vseth to bee in philology: Sir wee are not now in your element. And therefore no maruaile though you so much mistake your selfe. For who euer (that euer had any tast of philosophy) would make o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:2352:23"/>and affection the two heads of errour? when as euery error is nothing else but a false opinion. But if you would know the originall of false opinion, then may you make these two heads, and fountaines there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: Fancy, and affection: For fancy doth so print his markes in the vnderstanding, that it fashioneth it; and affection setteth so sharpe an edge vppon the will, that it is formed thereby: by both which meanes opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion is ingendered: which opinion is, as the markes bee, true or false, and as the edge is, good or bad. Which markes, if they bee not suted in the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staunce of the thinges; which edge if it bee not aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered in the qualities of the obiectes, they breed two vvandring and misled iudgemntes, vvhich bee errours and false opinions. For euen the vvil it selfe, whose ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect is, <hi>verum bonum,</hi> the true good: though it bee led by the good, yet is it tried by the truth. And vvhere the obiect to the affection seemeth to be good, if in conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of time it proue not truly so to be, the vvant of truth in the good causeth,
<note place="margin">Voluntas est extensus intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loctus ad ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bendum velfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciendum aliquid.</note> the vvil inlarged vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, to erre in iudgement, mistaking the apparent for the true good, which is nothing else but a false opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the good: And therefore we vse to say, not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out warrant of the truth: if vve conceiue vvel of a man whom experience proueth otherwise, or if vvee thinke hardly of any vvho sheweth the contrary in his dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling; vve had a false opinion of the man. If vvee loue one, vve haue (vve say) a good opinion of the man; if vve hate any vve haue a bad opinion: vvhich opinion either good or bad, beeing by contrarie experience found otherwise, our opinion vvas false, and our error manifest; and therefore is affection rather the father then the fellovv of opinion. And yet bee neither affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:2352:24"/>nor opinion simply and at all times cankers.
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. 2.</note> For opinion as it is oftentimes false, so it is sometimes true: and if hee make a true opinion the authour of errour, that is an errour; if false opinion, that is false: For false opinion is error; and nothing is or can be cause or au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour of it selfe.</p>
                  <p>And as for affection, it is neither good nor euill, but as it is vsed. If it bee bridled with reason, and vsed with moderation, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> worst affection is good: if without rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son it runneth at randome, the best is bad. The triall of an affection is all in the wearing. Indeede it may cause a false opinion helped by fancy, or by straining of it selfe; As fancy may do the like by helpe of affection, or by the strength of it selfe. So that wee will now ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to make a diuision of errours, ranging them into three rowes, 1. The Errors of fancy, 2. Errors of affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. 3. Errours both of fancy and affection, of which kinde, is the errour of the Moter in this place: which moueth him thus to hammer the two diuerse causes of the matter and efficient together. It is the counsell of fancie, and the current of his own affections, and no other thing, as the sequell will declare.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="motive">
               <head>The motiue.</head>
               <q>
                  <hi>THere is nothing of more manifest presumption then the truth of the scriptures, nor fuller of desire then se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of happines; therefore these two being left vnlimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the one of canonicall exposition, the other with ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessitie of meanes, are a direct methode of indirecte con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequence.</hi>
               </q>
               <div type="remove">
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:2352:24"/>
                  <head>The remoue</head>
                  <p>TO make good his diuision, he would faine giue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances, and pattern out his two errours with two practises or examples. But how he can bring manifest presumption, to errour in opinion, or securitie of hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinesse, to errour of affection, it passeth my vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: But yet that he would faine doe, as I perceiue by him, by leauing them vnlimited on our parte. As thus, the manifest presumption of the truth of the scripture is left vnlimited by them in wanting canonical expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition; the securitie of happinesse in hauing necessity of meanes. So that if we want we erre, if we haue we erre: whether we want or haue still we erre. But we will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere him in all pointes when we come to his parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular obiections. In the meane time for his obscurity; feare to be vnderstoode is an argument of distrust.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="motive">
               <head>The motiue.</head>
               <q>
                  <hi>SVch is the practise of the later religion, they teach that nothing is to be credited, but what is warranted in holy bookes, and giue not infallible rules of interpretation, but such as at last must be ouerruled by priuate opinion: for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of places, propriety of phrase, acceptions of wordes, can make no other conclusion then euery ones conceit wil aforde. So that of an infallible proposition, and arbitrary assumption, must needes insue a dangerous conclusion, though not euer in the matter which is concluded, yet al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies in the manner of concluding.</hi>
               </q>
               <div type="remove">
                  <pb facs="tcp:2352:25"/>
                  <head>The remooue.</head>
                  <p>IN the beginning of this speech I thought he had spo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken of themselues: for he nameth the later religion, which no doubt is theirs: which I could prooue by ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry sufficient arguments: but that I am partly of <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> his mind,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>De virginibus velandis c.</hi> 1.</note> that <hi>Haereseis non tam nouit as, quam veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas reuincit.</hi> Heresies are not so soone confuted for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing newe, as for being not true. And therefore leauing this let vs examine the rest of this period; which more truely toucheth vs, and commeth nearer to the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. They teach, saith he, that nothing is to be credited, but what is warranted in holy bookes: I assure you a shrewde obiection. Why then the Popes <hi>Legenda au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea,</hi> his legend of lyes, is nothing worth with vs, but to stop mustard pots? A sore matter, when such a saint as the Pope, shall beate his head for his owne benefit, to deuise masses, indulgences, trentals, pardones, &amp; pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, and you will not beleeue him, beleeue me your are to blame. You are but a young man, maister A. I hope his holinesse will pardon vs without a pardon, for holding with holy bookes. From whence hath he Peters keyes, Paule his sworde, Christ his wooden crosse, and his owne triple golden crowne, and his monkes monethly shauen crownes? Hath hee them not by warrant out of holy bookes? It standeth with his holinesse: I knowe hee hath: or else is he shamefully be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyed. What though Antichrist bee mentioned in the Bible? I hope you do not thinke the Pope to be him? What though in holy bookes the whore of Babilon be much like the Pope of Rome, and her beast like the city of Rome, and the seuen heades of her beast, as like
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:2352:25"/>as may be the seauen hilles of Rome,
<note place="margin">Reuel. 17.</note> as also the Angel expoundeth it? Yet welfare your canonicall expositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that shifteth all these to another shore; and blindeth the eyes of the simple with deuout ignorance &amp; igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant deuoutnesse, making them beleeue, that their on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly way to see, is to shut their eyes. But we are taught by another spirit to make the worde of God, a light vnto our feet, and a lanterne vnto our pathes. And this cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth vs to bee so simple, as neither to say nor doe any thing, neither yet to approue of any sayings or doings, without warrant from this word being throughly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded of this, that who so walketh without this light, stumbleth; and who trauelleth without this lanterne, falleth. This were well, if you would set downe some infallible rules of interpretation. Shall a man make a rule for a rule, or set vp a candle in the sun-shine? The worde of God of it selfe, vnto it selfe is a rule: what rule then keepe you for a rule? Would you haue leade for golde, or the leaden rule of mans inuention, for the golden rule of diuine inspiration? But the truth is, hee speaketh according to the very fashiō of their church: it is nothing with them if euery worde bee not a rule, squaring the word of God according to their worde; when their word should be conformed according to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> word of God.
<note place="margin">Ribera in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>as minores.</note> I lighted of late vpon one of their inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretours, who setteth downe an hundred, thirty and three rules for the exposition of the scripture: wherof scarce three of them be to any great purpose. Our men make the onely meanes to compasse the meaning of the holy Ghost, to be the knowledge of the tongues &amp; artes sanctified by the spirit of God: being furnished with which helpes our trust in God is, eyther in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalogicall, or anagogicall, historicall, or morall inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation,
<pb facs="tcp:2352:26"/>in one of these fower to find out the true and natiue meaning of most places in the booke of God. Neither be these expositions by these meanes accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilshed, to be accounted the conceits of priuate men: but rather the counsell of the true vicar generall of Christ,
<note place="margin">Marlorate.</note> which is the holy Ghost. For as the writing of the Septuagintes, being so many men differing in so fewe wordes, were knowne to be directed by the fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of God: So the consenting of many of our writers, iumping, and ioyning togither without iarre in one exposition, (as in our ecclesiasticall exposition appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth) doth certifie our consciences of the direction of the holy Ghost. Now what he meaneth by an infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble proposition, an arbitrary assumption, and a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous conclusion, I know not: vnlesse he would haue the church of Rome alone to frame the maior, the minor, and conclusion: which if he could once bring to passe, all the world should be papistes.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="motive">
               <head>The motiue.</head>
               <q>
                  <hi>IN like manner they promise security of saluation, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out respect of repentance and workes, which are ineuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble consequences, if all be true that they teach. So that hee which hath faith, needeth no more to care for good works, then they that haue dronken a sound purgation, for going to the stoole.</hi>
               </q>
               <div type="remove">
                  <head>The remooue.</head>
                  <p>WE will not be angry with these slanders, least wee should seeme to acknowledge them, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temning them they will weare out of themselues. But yet let me tell you this: wee do promise no securitie of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:2352:26"/>saluation, for it is out of our power, but Christ promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth it: whosoeuer beleeueth in me though hee were dead, yet shall he liue: he that beleeueth in me shal not perish, but haue life euerlasting: So that it is Christ and not vs that you repine at, in grudging at our securitie. Which securitie neuerthelesse wee teach not voide of works and repentance, for that were sottish: but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt or wauering, for that is truest. Faith, the seale of this security, can no more bee without repentance then the sunne without light, or the fire without heate. Faith the cause, repentance the effect: Faith the Tree, repentance the fruit: faith goeth before, repentance commeth after; after I say, not in succession of time, but in the order of causes. According to that rule of S. Paul: <hi>Quicquid non est ex fide peccatum est:</hi> whatsoeuer is not of faith, is sinne; euen repentance it selfe not <hi>ex fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de,</hi> not comming of faith, is sinne. This <hi>ex fide,</hi> out of faith, argueth a priority of faith: why then you will say, he that hath faith, may liue without care; for repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance commeth with it. I, but yet you must know, that where faith and repentance be, there must needes bee care. For the first of the seuen affections of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, in the second to the Corin. 7.11. is, great care. So that our security is not <hi>sine cura ite,</hi> goe without care, as the etimology seemeth to implie. For being wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked by repentance from the sinne of security, not to be secure bringeth vs the next way to security of saluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Thus is our security, not carnall but spirituall; not without care, but full of care. For where there is true faith, there is true repentance; and where is true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, there is a great care, not only to eschew euil, but to do good. As touching that beastly similitude wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he windeth vp this point, it is not worth the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming.
<pb facs="tcp:2352:27"/>Hee that toucheth pitch shall bee defiled there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with. It only serueth to set out vnto vs, as doung doth the stable, where dwelleth an vnclean spirit.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="motive">
               <head>The motiue.</head>
               <q>
                  <hi>THese are the two fallacies whereupon</hi> Luther <hi>builte his rebellion, and wherein all the heresies of our time conspire, though otherwise at difference with themselues: for there can be no fitter baites to beguile simple men, then opinion; and sensual men, then ease: because euery one lieth open to decay in his own vices.</hi>
               </q>
               <div type="remove">
                  <head>The remooue.</head>
                  <p>YOu speake but by hearesay: for this can I say: you neuer had, much lesse euer red al Luther, that you can iudge thus throughly of him. Such be his fallacies, that all the sophistry of the sea of Rome, either in his time, or since, could neuer bee able to aunswere them. And because you talke of baites, let vs compare our baites together, that wee may see which are the best fishers of men. You baite for simple men with igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance: but we baite for ignorant men with knowledge. Your baites for sensuall men, be indulgences: but our baite for carnall men is care. Now let the world iudge whether we or you flatter our selues most in our owne vices, and decay soonest in our own flatteries.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="part">
            <head>THE FOVRTH MOTIVE.</head>
            <div type="motive">
               <q>
                  <hi>AMongst many loadstones, that which hath the pree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minēce of vertue in proportionable distance, winneth
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:2352:27"/>the Iron frō al the rest: So Christ being lifted vp in the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>basing of his passion, promised by his attractiue virtue, to draw vnto his seruice, all men from al religions For what rebellion of nature cannot hee pacifie, vnto the vnity of Faith, when he pleaseth to come within compasse, that hath vnited humane nature into Gods hypostaticall vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Therefore to gather vp the effect as a threed, to leade to the cause, the greatest multitude in consent of commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion among the diuerse parcels and rentes of those that beare the liuery of Christ his name is a sufficient demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stration of the true and naturall loadestone, which must of necessitie drawe more vnto it then the rest, because it effecteth by his owne virtue, when all the rest worke on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie by the touch thereof.</hi>
               </q>
               <div type="remove">
                  <head>The remoue</head>
                  <p>IT is a worlde to see, <hi>quam ingeniosa nequitia,</hi> what a wit wickednesse hath:
<note place="margin">Mahomets tombe of Iron drawn vp by a loadstone and hanging in the ayre.</note> a strange deuise to drawe on a strong delusion. Howbeit, if this be all they haue to shewe: the deuise of the loadestone built Mahomets tombe before their temple; and the argument of mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude is more viewable in the churches of Turky, then of Italy. Christ is the loadstone, but all mettall is not Iron, that is, constant in affliction and firme in faith. More leade that beareth euery stampe, and tinne that windeth euery way, and copresse that carieth diuerse colours, then iron: some are too grosse to be drawn as lead, and some againe are too fine to be drawne, as sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer and gold: so that as most mettals cannot be drawn of the loadstone; so most men will not be drawne vnto Christ. Why then doth he promise to drawe all vnto him? whom he meant by that all I take it he telleth vs:
<pb facs="tcp:2352:28"/>
                     <hi>Iohn. 3.15.</hi> whosoeuer beleeueth in him he will drawe him vnto him, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he shal not perish but haue life euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting; or else as the cōmon answere is, <hi>genera singulorū,</hi> not <hi>singula generum,</hi> of all sorts some, not all and some: As the moter would haue it all men from al religions. Why then do they wrangle with vs? vvee are of their religion; why do we reiect the Iewes? they are of ours: vvhy do the Iewes contemne the Turks? they are al of one religion. If it be true that he saith that Christ hath drawn all men from all religions vnto his seruice: why doth he labour to distinguish the true from the false by multitude, when there is no difference at al? But indeed there is a difference, &amp; if you vvill needs make it in the nūber, it is in the paucity, &amp; not in the multitude: For that is Christ his own marke vvherby he knoweth his flocke. <hi>Luke 12.32. pusilla grex:</hi> Little flocke. Feare not little flocke, for it is your fathers pleasure to giue you a kingdome. And the Moter saith.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="motive">
               <head>The motiue.</head>
               <q>
                  <hi>THis populous inheritance, of such as professe the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of his doctrine, was giuen him as a royalty in the</hi> 2. <hi>Psalme. And after his resurrection he sent his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles to take possession of the dowry of his church, from Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rusalem vnto the ends of the world, and the prophets who from their heigh tower of speculation might ouerlooke more then the compasse of 2000. yeares, and therfore took the draught of Christ his kingdome, could perceiue no signe more glorious and visible, then a multitude reaching from the Easte to the West, and spreading ouer the earth. And yet for the straights of the throng putting vp supplica<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion to the church, to send some colones &amp; to enlarge their habitation.</hi> Angustus est mihi, fac spatiū mihi vt habitē.</q>
               <div type="remove">
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:2352:28"/>
                  <head>The motiue.</head>
                  <p>HEre the moter would faine intrench his multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, in the behalfe of their church within the safe garde of three places of scripture: but all in vaine. For first for his first place the second Psalme and 8. verse, &amp; the beginning of the verse, there is, as in many other places, mention made of the vocation &amp; calling of the heathen: which was fulfilled by the ministry of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles, but especially by <hi>Paule,</hi> who thereupon is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>doctor gentium,</hi> the teacher or doctor of the gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles; but there is no mention in that place of many or fewe. But yet hee to whom the offer in that place is made saith Mathew 22. Many are called, but fewe are chosen; whereout we may obserue two kinds of chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, with their two sortes of congregations. There is the called church, and there is the chosen church; and their congregations bee many, and fewe. The called church hath many in the congregation, but the cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen church but fewe. You will be called the church, or the called church, therefore is your congregation ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; but we are the chosen church, therefore is our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, fewe; that the scripture might bee fulfilled. And as for the latter part of that same verse: where the vttermost parts of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> earth, which are not so populous as the middle, are promised as a possessiō vnto Christ, that is nothing vnto them, but it is much vnto vs who are said euen by the poet to be vttermost of all people. <hi>Et penitus toto remotos orbe Britannos.</hi> And therefore the Pope placed the Archbishop of Canterbury at his right toe, <hi>Tanquā alterius orbis papam:</hi> as he said, As it were a Pope of an other world. So that his first place
<pb facs="tcp:2352:29"/>affordeth nothing but the calling of the heathen, wher in we haue as great a share as any, in that we are parte of the vttermost partes of the earth.</p>
                  <p>The second place is the 28 of Mathew, or 16 of Marke as I take it. And it is as well applied, as it was by frier Francis, aliás saint Francis, who (bicause our sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Christ in that place giueth in charge to his disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, to go out into all the world &amp; preach the Gospel to euery creature) went to the sea side, and preached to the fishes, and into the wildernesse and woodes, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the gospell vnto the beastes and birdes. The like threede of consequence the moter draweth out of the same place; that because after his resurrection he sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth his disciples to teach all nations, and to preach vnto all creatures, therfore the greatest companie is greatest liklihoode, to be the true church; framing his argument affirmatiue; which the Apostle maketh ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiue, Rom. 10. <hi>Sed non omnes:</hi> But all haue not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beied the gospell. And by a speach borrowed from the prophet Esayaes intimating that eyther fewe or none beleeue as they ought. Lord, saith he, who hath belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued our report? and therefore either fewe or none in comparison, be the note of the true church.</p>
                  <p>The third place which bordereth nearest vpon their ground, (though of another nature) is in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> 49. of Esay 20. <hi>Angustus est mihi locus, fac spatium mihi vt habitē.</hi> The children of thy barrennesse shall say again in thine eares,
<note place="margin">Straitned in her selfe, not inlarged be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond others.</note> the place is straite for me, giue place to mee that I may dwel. Where the church is not compared with other congregations, but with it selfe. In regard of the former desolations, persecutions, and afflictions, the church was barren, and without children: but there is a time of deliuerance there prophesied and promised,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:2352:29"/>after which the Church so increaseth and multiplieth, that she exceedeth the narrownes of her own breadth, and ouerreacheth y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> shortnes of her own length. And therfore although <hi>fac mihi locum</hi> giue me place, shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that she is straitned in her self; yet notwithstanding <hi>Angustus est locus,</hi> the place is straight: argueth no excessiue breadth in comparison of other places. Wherefore all that that place affordeth is a compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of times in the same church; and not a comparison of churches at the same time. And in my opinion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering the state of the church of Englād what it hath beene, and what nowe it is; there is not in all the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, a more pregnant place, to confirme the consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in this pointe in the truth of our religion, then this is being applied with the antecedēts. Thy builders make hast; thy destroyers and they that made thee wast are departed from thee, &amp;c. <hi>lege, intellige, collige.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="motive">
               <head>The motiue.</head>
               <q>
                  <hi>And because by diuine dispensation there were some seditions and factions to spring in his kingdom.</hi>
               </q>
               <div type="remove">
                  <head>The remooue.</head>
                  <p>This sauoureth much of Machiauel, to say, seditions come by diuine dispensation, is as if the maister of the house shoulde sowe discorde amongst his ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes, thereby to vnderstande the dealing of both factions. But he proceedeth.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="motive">
               <head>The motiue.</head>
               <q>
                  <hi>THat it might not breed admiration in the newe sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects by the nouelty or distraction of doubt, if the new
<pb facs="tcp:2352:30"/>parte might by number be mistaken. Therefore Christ &amp; his Apostles haue both foretold there should bee hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques, and branded them alwaies by the note of paucitie to be distinguished from the generall multitude. For they shall come vnder the stile of small and thinne numbers &amp; priuiledged places. There is Christ among the Caluinistes in Geneua. There is Christ among the Lutherans in Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many. In the desart for a thousand yeares since Phocas. In some secret of concealed doctrine, since the Apostles time. But beleeue them not, for not al, or the most part shall be apostate, but some, not many, but such as in compare of the whole multitude, shal be as errant planets in respect of the fixed starres.</hi>
               </q>
               <div type="remove">
                  <head>The motiue.</head>
                  <p>HAuing spoken for themselues, he would fain now speake against vs. Which he thinketh he doth by taxing of fewe, small, and thin numbers, as not fit for the seruice of the great King: and yet we reade in the reuelation that the most part of the world waite vpon the whore of Babilon: and the fewer or smaller number worshipped the Lambe of God. We are fewe, as that number that enter in at the straite gate, walke in the narrow way, and find euerlasting life. But we are not fewe, as those famous infamous heretickes, which came like great plagues one or two in an age. Englād, Scotland, Germany, Geneua, Denmarke, and a great part of France no contemned number, though wee contend not in number. There is Christ among the Caluinistes at Geneua, why not? a great deale sooner then at Rome; where there be the two infallible signes of his presence, the preaching of the worde, and right vse of the sacraments. There is Christ in the desarte:
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:2352:30"/>not vnlike; when the church was there, for the space of seauen hundred yeares or thereabouts, euen all the time of Antichrist his cheefe strength and tyranny. And this I take to be meant by the time, and times, &amp; halfe a time: <hi>Reue.</hi> 12:14: But to the woman, which is the church, were giuen two wings of a great Eagle, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> she might fly into the wildernesse, into her place where she is nourished for a time, and times, and halfe a time, from the presence of the serpent.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="motive">
               <head>The motiue.</head>
               <q>
                  <hi>THerefore this argument from the multitude of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municants in the same faith, promised by God, foreseen by the Prophets, confirmed by the Apostles, was esteemed of so sufficient proofe, by the primitiue cōmanders of Christ his church: that they vsed it alwaies against the hereticks: &amp; oftentimes when they were to encoūter they would brā<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dish this sword, as deadly &amp; vnauoidable, to amaze and yet not strike with it.</hi> Poteram omnes propositionum tua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum riuulos, vno ecclesiae sole siccare. <hi>For the experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment whereof if we turne ouer the successiō of histories age by age, we shal find that when any heresie was at the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est floud, it was not comparable to the ebbe of catholickes, no not in the torrent and inundation of the</hi> Arians <hi>by</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanasius <hi>testimony. Therfore we may presume the euent of that prophesie which hath so equally proceeded hitherto, and vsed for a weapon against the heretickes of our time, which hath bin so oftē died in the bloud of their ancestors, and followe our fathers herein which so happily followed others.</hi> Deo gratias.</q>
               <div type="remove">
                  <pb facs="tcp:2352:31"/>
                  <head>The remoue</head>
                  <p>HE that in Logicke concludeth vvithout a <hi>medium,</hi> reckoneth at his Inne without his oaste: both which the Moter doeth in this place. First his argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment wanteth a <hi>medium:</hi> for a multitude is not a fit <hi>medium</hi> to proue a church. But <hi>multitudo credentium,</hi> a multitude of them that beleeue, argueth the church: but that is forgot all this while. Secondly, he reckoneth without his oaste: for hauing wrested three places of scripture, to his own purpose, though contrary to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son: he maketh reckoning of them in this recapitula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or score of his proofes, promised by God, foreseen by the Prophets, confirmed by the Apostles: But aske the Apostles, the Prophets, and God himselfe, &amp; they vvill all, as one confesse, they knowe no such signe, or made no such score, as seuerally in their places wee made enquirie of. Yea, but the primitiue church vsed it alwaies against heretickes as a deadly and vnauoida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble sword. But yet it was but a florish of theirs, saith the Moter, they brandished it to amaze, but did not strike with it. What need I answere him when he answereth himselfe? they vsed it as deadly, and yet did neuer strike with it: if they did not strike with it, how knewe they it to bee deadly? If they knewe it to bee deadly, why did they not strike with it? They saide perhaps as the Moter saieth in this, <hi>Poteram,</hi> &amp;c. I coulde doe this, dry vp all your riuers of argumentes, with the sunne of the church. No, no, they were learned and godly men, and did both know, and acknowledge, that the true church consisteth not in outward shew but in inwarde substance: not in multitude of men, but in the truth of God: not in the name of catholikes, but in the nature of Christians.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="part">
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:2352:31"/>
            <head>THE FIFTH MOTIVE.</head>
            <div type="motive">
               <q>
                  <hi>THis new stamp of religion, which</hi> Luther <hi>&amp; his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters boast of to bee reformed according to the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient coine, cannot auoid the desert of counterfait.</hi>
               </q>
               <div type="remove">
                  <head>The remoue.</head>
                  <p>THis is the paradox or position which this motiue holdeth, to vvhich we answere affirmatiuely: <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spondetur quod potest:</hi> we answere, it can defend it selfe from the slaunder of counterfait. Nowe let vs see his cunning in prouing the contrary, though the manner of bringing in his position be out of frame, but we will not stand vpon words. <hi>His reason.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="motive">
               <head>The motiue.</head>
               <q>
                  <hi>BEcause so generall a reformation, and restitution of the primitiue church neither can be, neither was to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected.</hi>
               </q>
               <div type="remove">
                  <head>The remoue.</head>
                  <p>WHerein he seemeth by way of concession to grāt, that indeed the doctrine and discipline of the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue church was wholy corrupted and depraued by them both in matter of doctrine, and discipline of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. But their hope vvas, that so generall a reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and restitution could not be, and therefore grieued them the more because it was not expected: wherein I vvould faine shew you their blindnesse, and their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety. Their blindnesse, in that they would not see that
<pb facs="tcp:2352:32"/>God can do all things, hee can restore in a moment of time, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> which mā hath corrupted in a milliō of yeers, and that either with, or without means. Their impiety, in that they delighted in their rottennes, without loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king for recouery; thinking of God, because thēselues were so, as carelesse of his church. But he maketh shew of some reason in the words following, vvhich maketh me make the more haste.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="motive">
               <head>The motiue.</head>
               <q>
                  <hi>FOr although the worship of adulterous religion haue suffered many changes, either by the admiratiō of some man of extraordinary accoumpt, or the intimation of ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, or the ambition of superstitious, or inuasion of neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, or change of gouernement, the state alwaies fashio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning religion, the fittest consequence of policy: yet in the true religion instituted by God himselfe, the diuine ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance hath made onely two memorable varieties, not by condemning the former, but by preferring the latter, not in difference of substance but perfection: not by retracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as in change of their counsell, but adding of timely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse. The first was from the law of nature, to the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection of the law written. The second from the seuerity of the lawe, vnto the obedience of the Gospell (Christ be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the summe of al, but with difference.) For in the state of nature hee was discerned a farre off as a bodie. In the lawe hee was distinguished nearer as a man: In the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell he is seene face to face: Both these changes were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitutions of the former, but with some perfection. For</hi> Moyses <hi>restored the decalogue, sacrifice, worship of one God, circumcision, tenthes, Saboathes, and such like, which were in the state of nature but arbitrarie for har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:2352:32"/>In the Gospell Christ restored the interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the lawe which was corrupted, and the three great partes of religion. Iustification by faith, which was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amplified in Abraham. The sacrifice of himselfe, which was figured in Isaacke, and in the Pascha. The mysterie of baptisme, which was instituted in the deluge and redde sea, and the Eucharist which was acted by Melchise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deche.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>For like as when Thamar the daughter in lawe of Iuda brought forth her twinnes, Zaram and Phares, Zaram first put forth his hande, and the midwife tyed a red threed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it, and he pulled it in againe, and his brother Phares was borne before him: So the sacramentes of the Gospell, which are bound about with the red threed of Christ his passion, did first shew their hand in Abraham, and Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chisedech, but the sacraments of the Iewes were borne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>So that these two bee not changes but restitutions, and these are two earthquakes, regestred in the Scripture, prophecied of before, expected by the Church, brought in with prodigious signes, confirmed by the visible pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence of God in miracles. And one more we expect which shall change all thinges temporall, into eternall, at the ende of the worlde.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="remove">
                  <head>The remooue.</head>
                  <p>THe policy of nature in things without reason, dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couereth the reason, of the policy of this bauking the bush, where the nest is, a short complaining:
<note place="margin">The Lapwing.</note> but where it is not, much adoe, as if there it were. Woulde you find his nest? then take him at the first and shor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest, and let his longest and last alone. The first change
<pb facs="tcp:2352:33"/>of adulterous religion came, saith he, by the admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of some man of extraordinary account: &amp; was not this the first step to popery? when some bishoppes of y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> account in Rome were aduanced to the familiarity, and frendship of the emperours, <hi>Theodosius,</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantine,</hi> and such like: this gaue the first occasion of popery. After that, that which he speaketh of, the am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition of the supestitious increased it: For after the bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop was once thus aduanced to the frendship of Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours, then must the emperor take his crowne from the bishop and no other.
<q>—<hi>Sumit quo dante coronam: &amp;c.</hi>
                     </q> After this ambition, followed inuasion. The ambition of the superstitious to giue the crowne, turned to the inuasion of neighbours to get the crowne. After the emperour had made him his neighbour in placing him next vnto him, presently hee grewe ambitious, to giue him his crowne, and then traiterous to take his crowne from him. After inuasion of neyghbours, suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded the change of gouermente; The Emperour of Rome into the Pope of Rome, the empire into the popedome: which is as great change of gouerment as may be. And lastly see how they fashion religion, the fittest consequence of policy. For the authority of the Pope, it is the policy of their religion, to make the popes supremacy, the religion of their policy. For the Popes purse is purgatory, and pardons: for his pleasure stewes &amp; strumpets: for their doctrine neither schoole diuinity, nor preaching diuinitie, but politique diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie beareth all the sway. So that to find their nest go no further then the adulterous religion, which he spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of first: and there, or no where you may find these vncleane birdes. For all the rest of his talke is nothing
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:2352:33"/>else but to drawe you from this place least you should perceiue them. What then say you to the rest of his discourse? Nothing but what hath beene said of olde; <hi>Sine controuersia sapit:</hi> he is witty and learned therein, but to no purpose, cleane besides the controuersie.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="motive">
               <head>The motiue.</head>
               <q>
                  <hi>BEsides these neither the scripture mētioneth any more, neither the iudgment of the church &amp; fathers did ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect other.</hi>
               </q>
               <div type="remove">
                  <head>The motiue.</head>
                  <p>IT is not well done therefore of the church of Rome to bring in another, adding as it please them to the word of Christ, with a greater change therof, then the lawe written brought to the law of nature, or the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of Christ vnto the lawe written. For the latter of those is the ripening of the former. But this last of theirs exceeding the highest degree of ripenesse, what is it but rottennesse?</p>
                  <p>If you deny the matter: the case is plaine. For if you accounte that for one, which was but from the not writtē law vnto the law written: then may you as ease<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reckon that for another, which is from the written Gospel vnto the not written gospel traditions I mean, which you esteeme as true as the gospell). And sure, I think, if a book were written of your not written truth, it would rise to a greater volume then the gospell of Christ, and epistles of the Apostles. And therefore this is one addition, or, if you will, restitution, more then the scripture mentioneth, the church of God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, or the fathers did euer expect.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="motive">
               <pb facs="tcp:2352:34"/>
               <head>The motiue.</head>
               <q>
                  <hi>FOr what prophesie eyther in the old testament or in the newe made way for this reformation, after 1000. or 1500 yeares? What prodigious signes gaue the world war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Luthers comming? which of the creatures out of course gaue attendance at his birth? with what extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary power was he guarded? with what miracles was his doctrine graced? That a religion venerable for age, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine for succession, comely for order, admirable for vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, approued by experience, allowed by prouidence, confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by miracles, rooted in so many kingdomes, that neuer was doubted of but by heretickes, neuer saw change but by her enimies, should vpon one mans and such a mans credit, and authoritie without greater cause, without any cause, fly the worlde and leaue her kingdome and royaltie at the dispose of one Apostata and Monke and an incestuous monke.</hi>
               </q>
               <div type="remove">
                  <head>The remooue.</head>
                  <p>ALl prophetes both in the newe and in the olde testament make way for this reformation. For as euery falsehood maketh away the truth, so euery truth maketh way for the truth. But you perhaps would haue some particular places. First in the old testament the corruption of your religion is set out in the tearms of the abhomination of desolation spoken of by Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel the prophet: Dan. 9.27. And the reformation of our religion in the whole course of the 49 of Isayah, vnder the titles of reparation from ruine, recouery frō barrennesse and deliuerance from captiuitie. Againe in the newe testament the 17 of the Reuelation, both your abhomination and our reformation is so clearely
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:2352:34"/>prophisied, that though we were spurblind we need no spectacles to make the truth seeme greater. First in the 3.4.5.6. verses, the whore of Babilon is so liuely pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out in her seat, attire, riches &amp; qualities, that who hath any iudgment in colours, may easily see it to bee the picture of the Pope of Rome. Secondly the fall of Kingdomes and corruption of religion in the interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation is set out. And ten hornes which thou sawest are ten kinges which yet haue not receiued a kingdome
<note place="margin">a Sub imperato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re Romano.</note>, but shall receiue power as kinges
<note place="margin">b Cum pontifice Roman<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> at one hower with the beast. These haue one mind, and shall giue their power and authoritie to the beast. These shall fight with the Lambe, &amp; the Lambe shall ouercome them. &amp;c. 12:13:14: vers. The application of which explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion would set out vnto vs, both the number and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of those kinges, who were but as kings, because they had giuen their power and authoritie to the pope of Rome. Thirdly the recouery of the kinges and the reformation of religion in the 16 and 17 vers. And the ten hornes which thou sawest vpon the beast, are they that shall hate the whore, and shall make her desolate and naked, and shall eate her flesh, and burne her with fire. For God hath put in their hartes to fulfill his will, &amp; to do with one consent for to giue their kingdomes vnto the beast vntill the wordes of God bee fulfilled: what can be more plain for reformation? First he saith the ten kinges shalbe with the beast, and fight with the Lambe: and then afterwards, hee saith, they shall bee with the lambe, and fight with the beast: that is, as it is there expounded, they shall with one consent giue their kingdomes vnto the beast, vntill the wordes of God be fulfilled: &amp; then God putteth into their minds to fulfill his will. Which being happily begon by some
<pb facs="tcp:2352:35"/>of those kinges, God grant the other may take exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple by them and speedily may do the like. I might here shew that he hath out-dated the age of Popedome: but his absurdity in the next point is greater. <hi>Iudaei signa pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunt:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.</note> The Iewes require signes, saith the Apostle. The moter is become a Iewe, he will not beleeue the truth, vnlesse it be confirmed with signes &amp; wonders. Why, Luther did not preach himselfe, neither did he teach a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny new doctrine, but what had beene from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, that he needed any signes. The miracles of christ and his Apostles confirme his doctrine and our faith: for him onely teacheth he, and in him onely do we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue. Neither the errour of the ancient, nor the suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession of ambition, nor the order of superstition, nor vnity in malice, nor experience in craft, neither naugh tie prouidence, nor lieng miracles, neither yet vsurped authoritie ouer many kingdomes, without warrant ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the lawe of God, or lawe of man, shal win vs from our Christ to your Antichrist; from the lambe of God, to the whore of Babilon; from the sincerity of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, to the abhomination of desolation. Thus Luther moued, and thus stand we. <hi>Deo grtias.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="part">
            <head>THE SIXT MOTIVE.</head>
            <div type="motive">
               <q>
                  <hi>AS the cause is the patterne of the effects, vpon which ground saint Paule from the vnitie of Gods church buildeth the vnity of Faith: so may we go backwards from the difference of effects to deny the affinitie of the cause, and from the impossibilitie of vnion in faith, take awaie the possibilitie of dependance from God.</hi>
               </q>
               <div type="remove">
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:2352:35"/>
                  <head>The remoue</head>
                  <p>IT is an argument that the mistris is blinde who is led by her maides:
<note place="margin">Blind diuinity</note> what thinke you then of their diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, borrowing all their light from humanity? The first in this motiue is Philosophy, and after her commeth in diuinity treading in her steps.</p>
                  <p>First <hi>Aristotle,</hi> and then <hi>Paule:</hi> and vppon <hi>Aristotles</hi> ground commeth in <hi>Paul;</hi> as who would say, <hi>Paul</hi> hath purchased a plot of <hi>Aristotle</hi> to builde vpon. Christ saith that his church is built vpon his own rocke: but the Moter saith that <hi>Paule</hi> builte their Church vppon <hi>Aristotles</hi> grounde. If they haue no better euidence then this, I doubt their title is not good. For besides that the Philosopher neuer had the ground, whereon the church standeth in fee farme: the Apostle neuer bargained with the Philosopher. And besides both these, I am afraide, hee hath forged the deedes both of the philosopher and Apostle, to serue his owne turne. First for the philosopher; I do not remember that hee sayth the cause is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the forme, patterne, or example of the effect. But <hi>Qualis causa talis effectus:</hi> Such as the cause is such is the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. And yet euen this also is not to bee vnderstoode of all causes at all times. Not of the finall, for the intent of a man may be good, and yet his action euill, as hee that doth euill that good may come thereof. Not of the efficient; for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> carpenter is nothing like his house. And the double heate of the vpper and lower regions of the ayre, by the compassing of the contrary to it,
<note place="margin">Per antiperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>asin.</note> cause the cold of the middle region, where the clouds be. Not of the material and formal causes; for the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:2352:36"/>and forme be the effect: and nothing is like it selfe, but euery thing is it selfe. Onely this principle is to be vnderstood of the proper effect of the sole or solitarie cause: And therefore the nice pointes of curious philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sophy can lay downe no certaine ground for sound di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinitie. Secondly for the Apostle: I maruaile where we may find that place of Paule, where, vpon the former Philosophicall ground, he buildeth the vnity of faith from the vnitie of Gods church? There be two kindes of blindnesse, saith Tertullian, <hi>non vident quae sunt,</hi> when men see not those things that be, they are blind: <hi>Videre videantur quae non sunt,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Apologeti. cap.</hi> 9. Ephe. 4.5.</note> and when men seeme to see those thinges that are not, they are blind also. Paule buildeth the vnity of faith vpon Christ onely, &amp; that he cannot see: &amp; so he is blind. He buildeth it not vpon the vnity of the church which he seemeth to see: And thus as saith the same author, <hi>Duae species caecita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis facile concurrunt.</hi> He is doubly blind, which may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sely bee; for in the next wordes hee saith, <hi>they may goe backwardes,</hi> as true it is, blind men do, as soone as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes; but his meaning is as his wordes be, <hi>From the difference of effects to deny the affinitie of causes:</hi> And yet the selfe same sun, hardeneth the clay, and softneth the waxe; being one and the same cause not onely of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent but also of contrary effectes: but yet the rule hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in his causes and effectes; And from the impossi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie of vnion in fayth take away the possibilitie of dependency from God. Indeede true it is which Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian saith, <hi>Cui veritas comperta sine deo, cui Deus cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitus sine Christo, cui Christus exploratus sine spiritu sancto, cui spiritus sanctus accommodatus sine fidei sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento?</hi> To whome is the truth opened without God, to whom is God knowne without Christ, to whom is
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:2352:36"/>Christ made manifest without the holy Ghost, to whō is the holy Ghost giuen without y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sacrament of faith? So that this is the gradation of faith: where is the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of faith there is the holy Ghost, where is the holy Ghost there is Christ, where is Christ there is God. From whence we may also drawe the line of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendency from God: God in Christ by the holy Ghost through faith, combineth the faithfull into one mysti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call body which is the church, and draweth it vnto himselfe to be vnited vnto Christ the heade. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hauing the sacrament of faith, which is a suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent vnion, wee haue the holy Ghost, wee haue Christ, and by him effectuall dependency from God. As I will prooue in the next period, where hee labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to inforce the contrary, for that is the proper place of argument. Onely in this place I do but point the finger at it; as a note of obseruation that here is the verticall point that this motiue in the height therof climeth vnto.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="motive">
               <head>The motiue.</head>
               <q>
                  <hi>SVch is the religion of the protestantes which hath no certaine principle of vnity, and therefore lacketh the cognisance whereby true religion is knowne: for where there is not an infallible authority, which doth iudge and decide controuersies by remouing al occasions of doubt, and reply, and vnto which absolute obedience is tyed: there must needes be variety of iudgements and opinions, which cannot be tyed in one knot; for al vnity in particulars, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth from the vinty of some cause wherein all agree.</hi>
               </q>
               <div type="remove">
                  <pb facs="tcp:2352:37"/>
                  <head>The remooue.</head>
                  <p>THe protestants religion hath both the law of faith, <hi>lex fidei, articuli fidei,</hi> saith <hi>Tertulliā,</hi> and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of loue: A newe commandement giue I vnto you, that you loue one another saith our sauiour Christ: both these the protestantes haue: as may bee proued by their constancy in persecution, and consent in reformation: and therefore they want not that cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine principle of vnitie, whereby, as by a cognisance true religion is knowne. And as for that authoritie he speaketh of: we must knowe, that there is <hi>Rex,</hi> or <hi>iudex inter nos,</hi> a king or iudge amongst vs, whose go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment is outwardely to bee seene amongst vs: and there is <hi>Rex intra nos,</hi> a king within vs, whose kingdom is to be felt within vs in our hearts. Againe, the king or iudge that is <hi>inter nos,</hi> among vs, diuideth his power in <hi>ciuilem &amp; ecclesiasticam,</hi> into ciuill and ecclesiasticall gouernement. But neither of these Christ accepteth of. For Christ hee submitted himselfe to the ciuill au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, when hee paied tribute vnto <hi>Caesar:</hi> and then to the ecclesiasticall, when he was brought before the high Priests: and iointly he putteth them both backe, where hee saith to him, that would haue had him bid his brother diuide his inheritance with him, <hi>Quis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stituit me iudicem inter vos?</hi> who made me a iudge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you? And yet by the confession of the very hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Christ was borne a king:
<note place="margin">Luke. 2.2</note>
                     <hi>vbi est ille qui natus est rex Iudaeorum?</hi> where is hee, saie the wise men, which is borne the king of the Iewes? And by the superscrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Pilate himselfe Christ died a king: Iesus of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zareth king of the Iewes.
<note place="margin">Iohn. 19.19</note> Now then will you know the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:2352:37"/>authority which maketh Christians? It is not <hi>regnum inter nos,</hi> a kingdome amongst vs; for my kingdome is not of this world (saith Christ:) But it is <hi>regnum intra nos;</hi> the kingdome within vs, which is of greater au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie then that among vs.
<note place="margin">Our authority is greater then the Papists, if theirs were good.</note> For although mans king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome be of great force, as beeing <hi>regnum inter nos,</hi> a kingdome among vs; yet is it outwarde onely, and not within vs. But the kingdome of God is spiritual, holie, and within vs. And what other authority was there I pray you among the Apostles? Was Peter the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles Pope, and yet checked to his face by Paul? what o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther authority in the primitiue church? was there ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Pope, or councell, but such as was voluntary with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out call or commaundement of any one? And yet all controuersies brought to a better passe then the pope can euer bring them vnto: because the authority was inward and not outward, in heart and not in wordes. It is no meruaile though men without all religion, haue notwithstanding a care of their actions: for there is <hi>lex fraeni</hi> for that, mans lawe to bridle them in that case. And politicke wise men will goe yet further, they will not onely haue an eye vnto their handes, but they will haue a care of their tongue also, that it bee not an Hebrew-English tongue, that is <hi>Lashon,</hi> which in He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew signifieth the tongue, and is English for the vice of the tongue. And they haue some reason likewise for this: for the law of man an outward gouernement, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth hould of words as well as of works. But tell me I pray you, if you can, what is the cause why some men haue a respect vnto the thoughts of their mindes to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straine and bridle euen them also? So that although sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan indeuoreth to suggest into them, <hi>Cogitationem ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li,</hi> the thought of an euill thing: yet they will striue so
<pb facs="tcp:2352:38"/>against it, that they wil not permit it to be <hi>Cogitationem malā,</hi> an euill thought (as one of the fathers speaketh.) No other reason can bee rendred hereof, but <hi>spiritus dominatur in conscientijs,</hi> the spirit of God raigneth in their heartes and consciences, and the scepter of that kingdome (which is the feare of God) beateth downe all sinne in them: as with <hi>Ioseph</hi> who would not sinne, though secretly, and with preferment, because he fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red God. There is not, nor euer hath beene, that I can read of among vs, any positiue lawes against othes &amp; ordinary swearing in common talke: And yet wee see and know that there be some men, that be as careful to refraine their tongue from swearing, as to obserue any of the princes lawes, and will be drawn as soone to kill a man, as to sweare an oath: and this is nothing but <hi>Christus habitat &amp; dominatur in corde,</hi> Christ dwelleth and ruleth in their hearts: and this lawe of Christ in the Gospell, <hi>Sweare not at all: neither by heauen, for it is the seat of God: neither by the earth, for it is his foot stoole:</hi> standeth in as full effect, force and strength with them, as any lawe or statute of any prince whatsoeuer: this is our dependency from God: this is the authority that ruleth vs in our actions, and ouerruleth vs in our opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions and iudgements: this is <hi>sacramentum fidei,</hi> the sacrament of our faith, wherein, according to the olde Romane <hi>Sacramentum militare,</hi> sacrament of war, wee giue vp our names, and take our oathes to be true vnto our heauenly king, and as good souldiors, manfullie to fight the Lordes battaile: whereby wee are vnited as many soldiours into one bande, hauing one captaine, one Lord, one God, one maister and sauiour, who is in and ouer all: <hi>Halleluiah.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="motive">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:2352:38"/>
               <head>The motiue.</head>
               <q>
                  <hi>BVt there is no such infallible authority, the iudge of controuersies, besides the voice of the church, which the protestants either put altogether to silence, or else obey so far as they please: for the scriptures, whom they haue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to be iudges, as rebels that put down all iudges, and pretend to be ruled onely by the lawe, which cannot alone supply this place, to take away all occasions of controuersies.</hi>
               </q>
               <div type="remove">
                  <head>The remoue.</head>
                  <p>SHoulde a man beleeue the wife that differeth from her husband? Or shoulde a man giue eare vnto her that wrangleth, chideth, and telleth lies of him that should bee her best beloued? no more can the prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants obey the voice of that church that differeth frō Christ, or desire to know her pleasure, that careth not to please her spouse. As for the scriptures, wee knowe them to bee the reuealed will of God; and erected by God, and not by vs, as the onely touchstone to try the truth by. But yet we do not (as the Moter challengeth vs) put down all iudges. For we haue our ecclesiastical iudges, for the discipline of the church, and our mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators in diuinity, for the doctrine of faith; both as dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet in gouernment, and as learned in iudgement as any they haue. Onely this is the difference betweene theirs and our iudges: They, as tyrants, woulde haue their censure aboue the lawe ouer the scripture: wee as subiectes, iudge out of the lawe by the scripture: And therefore they are more like to outlawes then wee to Rebels.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="motive">
               <pb facs="tcp:2352:39"/>
               <head>The motiue.</head>
               <q>
                  <hi>ANd if there were no other argument their own irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliable quarrels, in so manifold differences among themselues, might suffice to stop their mouthes herein.</hi>
               </q>
               <div type="remove">
                  <head>The remoue</head>
                  <p>SAy there be some small iars in matters of discipline among vs, doth this ouerthrow our religion? Bee all of yours of one minde? whence then come the diuers names of Thomists and Scotistes, of white and blacke friars? who differ as much in opinions often times as colours. And the Iesuites (who like <hi>Scipio</hi> subduing <hi>Africa</hi> was called <hi>Africanus,</hi> so tooke they their name) bee as peeuish as any Puritan with vs. But in the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of faith we go all hand in hand together: and so long as the substāce of doctrin remaineth, the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staunce of discipline canne make no rent in Christ his coate <hi>Articuli fidei lex fidei:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">De virgin ibus velandis:</note>
                     <hi>Hac lege manente caeterae iam disciplinae &amp; conuersationis admittunt nouitatem correctionis, operante scilicet &amp; perficiente vs{que} in finem Gratia Dei:</hi> The articles of our faith, be the law of faith: which law remaining other matters of discipline, and conuersation do admit the nouelty of correction, the grace of God working and profiting the church vnto the ende, saith <hi>Tertullian.</hi> Which articles, which lawe of faith, all Israell, that is, all the faithfull, carry into the house of the Lorde God onely:
<note place="margin">How wee hold the articles of our faith, and how y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> papists.</note> vvhich the Philistins, that is, the superstitious, doe place in the house of Idols and images.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="motive">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:2352:39"/>
               <head>The motiue.</head>
               <q>
                  <hi>FOr as diuers parcels of silke of deeper or lighter ground, dipped by the dyar in the same liquour, drinke in a seue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall tincture of colour according to their former varietie: So they that diue in the letter of the holy scripture, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as their iudgementes are before stained with preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of one or other opinion; come forth again not in vnity of mindes, but in the same differences as they went in, more or lesse. Or as the miracle of tongues, giuen to the Apostles, when many auditors of diuers languages came to heare them: although the same men coulde speake no more but one idiome at once: yet the seuerall auditours comprehended them as if they had spoken in the propriety of their speach: So that when many of diuers languages in religion, come to heare some one of the Apostles speaking in the scripture, although the author vse only the voice of the truth, yet euery sundry faction, doth conceiue him as speaking in the seuerall confusion of their opinions.</hi>
               </q>
               <div type="remove">
                  <head>The remooue.</head>
                  <p>AS to the bleare eyes the light of one candle,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Tertull. cen. Mar. lib.</hi> 1.2,</note> by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiding the sight thorough the eyes weakenesse, not multiplying the light in the increase of it selfe, see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth many: So to an erroneous iudgment, the truth of one religion (through the manifolde boutes and win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinges of its own conceit, not by any receit of change in the truth it selfe) seemeth diuers. Sir, your silke is not good, or your colours not good, or your lucke not good: for no man will buy any that hath but halfe an eye of faith. For you see in your silke the difference of
<pb facs="tcp:2352:40"/>the die, commeth from the diuersity of the grounde. But our ground is one, our doctrin the same, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no colours but one, as the church serueth them out. But if in the wearing of this silke, in the practise of this doctrine in our discipline, there seemeth in some fewe, some alteration in the skirtes, or vtmost partes: they sure bee some staines through the parties negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, and no variety either in ground or colour (you shall see) if you see not the colours of your owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits. Not many groundes, but one, our catechismes and institutions lay downe; not many colours, but one our commentaries, and expositions vnfould. Take all our catechismes, (which be many) and you shall finde much variety of inuention, but none of iudgement: many waies in one ground. Take al our commentaries, which bee your colours out of the scriptures die: and you shal perceiue some better glosse in some, and some quicker brightnesse in others; but <hi>idem est omnium can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor,</hi> the light of the truth is alike in all.</p>
                  <p>I appeale vnto your own conscience, whether there is not more forcing of the scriptures both by corrupt translations, &amp; adulterous expositions in your writers then in ours. If you will not speake: that one place, the mother promise of all Gods promises, the thirde of <hi>Genesis</hi> and fifteene shal speak for vs. Looke vpon that place, as it is wronged by your expositours and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slatours, and looke vppon the rest of the promises of God, children of the same parents, like themselues and their parents, and you shall see, you haue made it with your ridiculous superstitions, neither like it selfe that is the truth, nor like the rest of the promises, wherof that was the first. Read in iudgement, and not in affection your own Rhemish testament, and tell me what fonde
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:2352:40"/>translations, and what foolish consequences you finde there. Compare the whole rabble of popish interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, <hi>Thomas, Scotus, Lyra, Hugo Cardinalis, Ihonsenius, Ribera,</hi> and the rest, with one <hi>Caluin,</hi> or, if that name mislike you, <hi>Musculus:</hi> if there be not more of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, and naturall meaning of the holy ghost in that one, thē in them al, <hi>&amp; Phillida solus habeto:</hi> And yours only shall be the church. This will I maintaine by ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument against the Moter with the wager of my life and deerest bloud. As for the rest of our expositours, though there bee distance sometime in their country, yet no difference in their colour. But as the miracle of tongues hath in one voice many languages, and in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny languages one truth so likewise bee there for vs, in one word many expositours; and in many expositours one religion, and colour of the truth.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="motive">
               <head>The motiue.</head>
               <q>
                  <hi>NEither can they comfort themselues with any hope to see these diuerse opinions wound vp in one confession: for as the vnity in conclusion in logicke, cannot bee with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the vnity of the</hi> medium; <hi>so they cannot meet in that middle way which should bring them in peaceable compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition, vnlesse they returne to the church; for all graunt there is no way to accomplish it without a councell: but who shall call it when there is none whom they all obey? How many factions shall assemble? out of what sect shal the president be chosen? what number of suffrages shall there be on euery side? what rule shall bee allowed for the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of the scriptures? And if al this were by a dreame imagined; yet the authority of the canons, and conclusions shall not bee so authentical; but that any priuate head may
<pb facs="tcp:2352:41"/>refuse it if in his owne singularity, he thinke it disagree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the scripture: so desperate is the possibilitie of v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion among them that hope, which imagineth impossible thinges, cannot possibly imagine it.</hi>
               </q>
               <div type="remove">
                  <head>The remooue.</head>
                  <p>THe languishing comfort of dry expectation is the onely prop of a broaken state: but where the state is whole there is comfort enioying it selfe. One com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort wee want, the comforte of wanting; another wee haue, the comfort of hauing: that web of conclusiones confession is already wouen with vs: and euery one that taketh charge in the church,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Anglicana con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>io.</hi> The booke of articles red by euery parson vpon instituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> doth vnfould euery parcell thereof, making open profession of that recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued confession. And therefore as Tertullian speaketh of the fancy of that heretique <hi>Marcionis deus,</hi> Marci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons god: so may wee say of his folly, <hi>ecclesia Motoris,</hi> the moters church is neither needfull nor heedefull, as the meres of middle way to bring vs to peaceable composition wherein wee dwell already. Wherfore mistaking his ground, his questions that follow crie all ayme to a wrong marke. For he taketh this as graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, which wee still denied, that our church is greatly disordered, and out of frame by reason of controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies and want of confession. And thereupon inferreth: <hi>that all graunt that there is no way to accomplish peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble composition without a councell:</hi> when as that councel was called when that booke of articles was compiled. But yet following his folly, hee proceedeth. <hi>But who shall call it when there is none whom they all obey?</hi> If hee meane this of the church of England, hee is no true subiect: for we all (except papists) obey one prince.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:2352:41"/>If he meane of the whole church of protestantes, he is no good Christian: for we all (except hypocrites) obey one Christ. And therefore the prince of the countrey, or some one by commission from him, may call a coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, (as Ambrose did in Italy vnder the emperour) to stint the controuersies that shall arise in his domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: whereupon if any fault shalbe, euery one amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one, all shall be well; and I do not doubt, but these nationall councels haue from Christ the same obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for the spirit of truth which the generall haue: <hi>vbicun{que}:</hi> Yea and if I should say more effectuall, I thinke I should not much ouershoote my selfe: for Christ his promise is <hi>duo aut tres,</hi> to two or three; for if there be many, many times <hi>maior pars vincit melio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem,</hi> the greater ouercommeth the better parte, as in those generall councels somtimes it came to passe. Whereby I am bold to say the obligation, <hi>vbicunque,</hi> is as good, if not better, for the prouinciall then gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall synods; so the same condition be obserued which is required of both, <hi>in nomine meo,</hi> in my name, saith Christ. For then Christ himselfe is president of that councell: <hi>where two or three are gathered togither in my name, there am I in the middest of them,</hi> which answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to another question of the moter; <hi>who should be the president of our councels?</hi> But first he moueth another doubt: <hi>How many factions shall there assemble?</hi> And to put him out of that doubt, not so many as in Italy: where euery head is a faction. For as in a garden of spices, euery thing that in taste and smell sauoureth not of the spice, being separated by nature, is reiected as a weede:
<note place="margin">Can. 4.16.</note> so in the Church (which is accounted in the scripture as a garden of spices) euery one that in life and doctrine relisheth not of the spirit, being deuided
<pb facs="tcp:2352:42"/>from the truth, is no better then a faction.</p>
                  <p>So that the members of a spirituall faction be simi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar like the parts of fier or water, where of euery parcell beareth the name of the whole. Because in euery one of this faction, there be many whose fact is one, manie affections, many thoughts, many motions both of the will and vnderstanding, which wholy combine them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues against the truth:
<note place="margin">Mark. 5</note> therfore may such an one imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate that foule spirit of the Gaderens, and say, my name is faction, for wee are many. And first for their liues, the Italian figs, their female if not their male stwes, their ambitious prelates, and their carnall Cardinals doe shewe of what spirit they bee. And as for their doctrine, read the scriptures, read the fathers, and you shall finde that it is not. Reade Wickliffe, Iohn Husse, Luther, Caluin, Beza, Whitakers, and Iewell, and you shall see it ought not. Read some of their own, Caietan and Ferus, and you shall knowe euen by them, manie points need not. Nay reade the conscience of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in these his writings, and you shal perceiue it was no point of doctrine (for hee toucheth not one in all his motiues that made him to turne his coat: but his only quarrel to vs, is that which Tacitus calleth <hi>complemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tū accusationis,</hi> the accomplishment of euery accusati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in the tyrannous times of <hi>Tyberius,</hi> to wit, <hi>Crimen miestatis,</hi> that wee obey not the bishop of Rome: this moued him not to obey our lawes, not to be obedient vnto our Christ and his annointed. This is the som of all his motiues, which he might as well haue set down in two words, as in seauen motiues. Let thē not ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore charge vs with factions, wheras y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> whole body of their religion is nothing but faction. And let vs call e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery thing in his proper name, acknowledging with vs
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:2352:42"/>some contention for the truth; and with them a great faction against the truth. There bee yet more doubtes: for hee is full of doubtes. <hi>Out of what sect shall the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sident be chosen? What number of suffrages shall bee on e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery side? What rule shal be allowed for the interpretation of the scriptures?</hi> All these be carefully prouided in our national synodes: and why then may they not bee as well ordered and disposed, if a general councel should bee called of all protestants? But all these doubts doe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rise in him from distrust of the assistance of Gods spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and for want of affiance in the promises of Christ. But we grounding vpon the worde of God, comming together in the name of Christ wee make Christ our president, and his vice-president who pleaseth him: for the number of suffrages, we leaue y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> to the direction of the spirit: and the rule of interpretation the analogie of faith. This is such a dreame, good sir, whereinto if your church could once fall, it would presently awake from that superstition, ambition, and auarice, wherein it hath slept night and day for a long time, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in surely the Moter lyeth; for now you shall heare him speake like one that talketh in his sleepe, and knoweth not what he speaketh. <hi>So desperate, saith he, is the possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of vnion among them that hope, which imagineth impossible things, cannot possibly imagine it.</hi> Heare you him what hee prateth? hope imagineth impossible thinges. I haue red that hope seeth inuisible thinges, but that it imagineth impossible things, I neuer either heard or read of such an hope. What cause hath it to imagine such things? why none: then can it not hope. I but it hath good cause to imagine them: then be they not impossible. He spitteth fire and water at once. For hope cannot be without good cause: and impossibility
<pb facs="tcp:2352:43"/>cannot bee with any cause. There is both possibilitie and probability in all hope: else it is but a bastard hope.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="part">
            <head>THE SEAVENTH MOTIVE.</head>
            <div type="motive">
               <q>
                  <hi>THe diuine prouidence which as a center indifferntly extendeth it selfe to the vniuersalitie of thinges, hath allowed euery creature a common strength to preserue his being; such is in liuelesse bodies their place or motion or qualities; in vegetable their instinct of distinguishing their proper aliment; in beastes, the iudgment of sence, &amp; priuiledge of nature, and in man an apprehension, censure and proiect, from the intelligence of sensible occurrents, both in naturall and ciuill bodies.</hi>
               </q>
               <div type="remove">
                  <head>The remooue.</head>
                  <p>THey that defend a bad case, must pretend a good cause: many high wordes set on a great face: but the simplicitie of the wise giueth a true grace. As hee that shooteth at the sunne though he bee well assured he shall neuer hit his marke, yet is he sure of this, that he shooteth hygher then hee that aymeth but at a dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie: So likewise the moter passeth through all the pathes of the prouidence of God, to search for their church and religion where he knoweth it neuer came nor will, that at the least he might be said to haue ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured as farre, and as faire as euer any did. For who e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer did seeke for darknesse in the light, or for falsehood in the truth, or for the prouision of the deuill in the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:2352:43"/>prouidence of God, but with the same minde as hee that set Dianaes temple on fire to be famous thereby?</p>
                  <p>And yet this is the quest of the moter in this mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, and to this end only maketh'he much of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence of God, as the sequell will shewe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="motive">
               <head>The motiue.</head>
               <q>
                  <hi>THe same wisedome and bountie which hath beene so enlarged to his seruantes, cannot bee straitened to his children: and therefore it is aboue all doubt that hee hath set downe some plaine and certaine direction in his church, both of discerning of heresies, when they arise, and of auoding the infection of them: Neither hath the holy Ghost failed herein, for because all the dangers of the church were cheefly to come from heretickes, hee hath drawne in the scripture as in a table the picture of here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes, their apparrell, faction, speach, and carriage where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they might be noted vpon the first appearance. But a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all other items, none is oftener giuen for a marke to discerne them then their difference of doctrine, from the former tradition and custome.</hi>
               </q>
               <div type="remove">
                  <head>The remoue.</head>
                  <p>WIthout all controuersie the prouidence of God alwaies watcheth, as an eye that at no time slee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth, and the bountie of God euer giueth as an hand that neuer faileth. And this also in some sort wee may grant, that this eye of prouidence is more watchfull ouer man then ouer other creatures, and this hand of bountie more plentifull vnto his children, then vnto his seruants (although the true children and seruants of
<pb facs="tcp:2352:44"/>God differ no more then the two sutes of obedience, loue, and feare, being but as the christian and surname of the same thing) for the loue of obedience is feare to displease, and the feare to dispease is loue to obey; the feare of loue maketh the children, &amp; the loue of feare maketh the seruants of the most highest. Further also we graunt that for the preseruation of the church and children of God, there is by the holy Ghost set downe not onely <hi>tesser a hospitalis,</hi> the inuiting signe in matters of spirituall commodities, as <hi>Selah</hi> in the psalmes; and <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> he that hath an eare, let him heare in the gospell: but also <hi>tessera hostilis</hi> the fighting signe in matters of danger, as markes in the sea to auoide shipwracke: As Christ his <hi>cauete,</hi> beware of false pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and the Apostles his <hi>absit,</hi> God forbid, so often repeated to call vs from calamitie. By both which signes it is more then euident that the preseruation of the church hath (aboue other thinges) both a watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full eye to keepe it, and a mightie hand to vphold it from falling to vtter confusion. But herein wee differ, this we deny; that as the liuelesse bodies by their place, motion, or qualities; the vegetable dodies by their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinct of nature; the beastes by the iudgement of sence, and man by the excellency of his vnderstanding: so the church by the former tradition &amp; custome should be preserued in her state. I confesse the first, I deny the former custome to be a signe of true religiō. For <hi>primū</hi> and <hi>optimum conuertuntur,</hi> the first, and the best, the best and the first is all one. In the state of nature first in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency, and then corruption; in the state of grace first integritie and then impietie. But as for the former, which in regard of the first may bee the latter, digres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing from the first goodnesse, as the church of Rome did from the primitiue church, the corruption gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:2352:44"/>by custome doth no more commend it, then the filth doth y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sore that long hath festered. And as a sicke man recouered will not praise the state of sicknes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the former: So religion reformed may not brag of custome in corruption, admit it were the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. So that thus y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> case standeth, we differ in doctrine not from the first, but from the former custome y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from the first. And customes plea of prioritie is not good but from the first.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="motive">
               <head>The motiue.</head>
               <q>
                  <hi>THere shall bee false teachers which shall bring in he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resies. Peter</hi> 1.2.</q>
               <div type="remove">
                  <head>The remoue.</head>
                  <p>HOw this place fitteth his purpose, I confesse my simplicitie I cannot conceiue. For if the bringing in of false religion ouer and aboue the true religion be heresie, then is the addition of their tradition heresie. But if the bringing in of the true, by thrusting out of the false bee the way of trueth, then is ours no he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resie. The proofe of both is that triall which both standeth to. We would haue our religion tried by the word of God, and writinges of the apostles, which is the onely true, and truly auncient religion; they will be tried by the word of the Pope, and the allowance and approbation of the church of Rome; which is wholy sowred with the leauen of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Pharisies, th'ambition of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> prelates: in one word this is the argument. If we did ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ad to or inuert y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> first forme of doctrine we would refuse to be tried by it, if they did not they would not refuse. And mark I pray you how he bringeth a rod to beat himself withal: for read y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> secōd ver, of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same chap &amp; you shall see, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the multitude which hee alloweth
<pb facs="tcp:2352:45"/>as the <hi>medium</hi> of his argument in the fourth motiue to proue the church, the Apostle allotteth as a signe to set heretikes out by. But this by the way though som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what out of the way, I thought good to obserue▪ His nexte place is.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="motive">
               <head>The motiue.</head>
               <q>
                  <hi>IF any man come to you and bring not this doctrine,</hi> Iohn. 2.10.</q>
               <div type="remove">
                  <head>The remooue.</head>
                  <p>I Hope you take not this verse for any of the popes ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, neither this doctrine for the doctrine of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ, the doctrine of worshipping of images, inuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of saints, praier for the dead, masses, purgatory, or any such stuffe shipped from hell, &amp; shopped at Rome: But the rule of dependency of places teacheth vs, that by this doctrine is meant nothing but the doctrine of Christ, whom we acknowledge for our sole mediator, without any merit of ours or helpe of any other, this I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of the father we worship, this <hi>sanctum sanctorum</hi> we only cal vpon, there is true purgatory and no where else. And therefore for the trial of doctrines: Shew me any doctrine, and I will shewe you Christ his question to the pharisies to resolue you in the truth of it. <hi>Cuius est imago, &amp;c.</hi> whose image and superscription beareth it? if you say your doctrine beareth Christ his image, then giue vnto Christ those thinges that are Christs, that is faith, loue, obedience. If you say it beareth the image of the whore of Babilon the church of Rome, then giue vnto the whore those things that belongeth
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:2352:45"/>vnto her, that is, pride, ambition, couetuousnesse, and superstition, as well you do. He that is pure, let him be pure still, and he that is filthy, let him be filthy still; and by this may be tried who bringeth this doctrine.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="motive">
               <head>The motiue</head>
               <q>
                  <hi>ANd the tradition of Corah.</hi> Timo. 1.5. <hi>If any man teach otherwise then that which you haue heard from the beginning, let it abide in you, fight for the faith once deliuered, keepe the traditions you are taught.</hi>
               </q>
               <div type="remove">
                  <head>The remoue.</head>
                  <p>THe tradition of Corah was against the ordinance of God, not the inuentions of men: wickedly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious to the lawfull magistrates of their own nation, and not iustly resisting the vsurped authority ouer al o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther nations. Of which authority and y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> doctrin therof (that wee may cut his throat with his owne sworde) Christes verdict may truely bee giuen; <hi>non erat sic ab initio,</hi> it was not so from the beginning. And therefore both that authority, and the doctrine built thereupon falleth to the grounde, as beeing neither knowne nor heard of frō the beginning. The rest of this place deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phereth out some hard mischance: for eyther the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor hath mangled the place, or the writer hath mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the authour: for there remaineth nothing but a spittle sence, where I leaue it.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="motive">
               <head>The motiue.</head>
               <q>
                  <hi>ANd if any will fashion in his wishes a plaine and sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible rule, whereby the thickest conceits are not able to
<pb facs="tcp:2352:46"/>go betweene truth and the loosest controuersies might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine any question, there cannot bee a better fancied then this difference of teaching, and innouation of doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, which hee that vnderstandeth not the sense may perceiue by the wordes, the soundes, and contradiction of former opinion. As men that are skilful in musicall propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that being acquainted through vse of song, can easily iudge if any change be made therein. By this were all he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resies apprehended at the first, and also arraigned; So that</hi> Stephanus <hi>bishop of Rome ouerthewe the decree of the councell of Carthage, for rebaptising, wherein saint</hi> Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian <hi>was president with his own rule:</hi> Ecclesia dei non habet talem consuetudinem.</q>
               <div type="remove">
                  <head>The remooue.</head>
                  <p>VAriety is good, so it be of good: but variety of euil is the diuels banket. Say me, what variety cal you this? fashion, fancie, falshood, conceit, deceit, custom, and cosenage, which bee the dishes for this seruice. First for fashion, it is the threedbare fashion of all ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholickes to face their faction with the title of the olde religion: when (as God knoweth) their religion hath not liued, nor continued the age of one man of the old world, neither came, to the age of <hi>Methuselah,</hi> beeing not yet nine hundred yeares ago since first it came to light. When as our religion (which they call newe) hath all one beginning with the beginning of all: wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse the first of <hi>Iohn</hi> Epist and Gospell, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>that which was from the beginning, &amp;c.</hi> that is, the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, middle, and end of all our doctrine; which is not so with them. Secondly, their olde fashion is se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conded with a newe fancy; for hee fancieth out a rule
<pb facs="tcp:2352:46"/>which is but a fancy: To wit the difference of teaching, and innouation of doctrine, which indeede speaketh plainly, that either yours or ours is hereticall. But to say that whatsoeuer differeth from your tradition is heresie, is the idle worke of fancy, finding no ground in the vnderstanding. On the other side; if you meane a difference of teaching, and innouation of doctrine, contrary to the Patriarkes, Prophets, disciples, and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles, of our sauiour Christ, therein appeareth your falshoode. For wee desire no other triall then the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the Patriarks, prophets, disciples, &amp; Apostles, the fathers of all ages moderating the matter in points of greatest difficulty. Fourthly, it is a strange conceite of his to sound the depth of doctrine, by the sound; or to trie religion by the eare onely. This is his conceite, and his deceit is to seduce the simple, that hee which vnderstandeth not the sence, saith he, may perceiue by the words, the sounds and contradiction of former o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion. O subtlety, why art thou so simple? O simpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, why art thou so subtile? Subtlety thou art to goe about to deceiue the simple with bare wordes and sounds, neither conceiued nor vnderstoode, as with a charme to bewitch and amaze them. Simplicity, thou art to men of vnderstanding, that they that vnderstand not the inwarde sence should iudge by the outwarde sence. As though wordes were any thing, without things but winde, <hi>verba symbola rerum,</hi> wordes bee the circumstances, thinges the substaunce; circumstance without substaunce what make you of that? wordes without thinges what thinke you of this? There is no braine in this; that men that vnderstand not the sence should be led as by a lanterne-man by the sound. Sixt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hee pleadeth custome (the continuance to wit of
<pb facs="tcp:2352:47"/>their contagion) as if to anger vs he would shame him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe. Tell me, doth custome prescribe as well against, as without law? Indeede, in cases of tithes and church priuiledges, the Ciuilian saith: <hi>vbi deficit consuetudo recurrendum est ad ius commune.</hi> Where custome fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth we must haue recourse to the canon Law: Making law to come in, where custome goeth out. But y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> diuine saith in matters both of doctrine and discipline. <hi>vbi deficit lex recurrendum est ad consuetudinem:</hi> where the law giueth ouer we must looke vnto the custom of the church. Where the word of God is silent (as some times of purpose to leaue some things arbitrary to the church) there the custome of the church preuaileth much. Not where there is <hi>scriptum est,</hi> the expresse word of God as a law &amp; rule to ratifie any thing; there to bring in contrary practise, and to prescribe that practise for a custome to all posterity, (as you doe in many, nay most, nay all pointes controuerted between vs) that is not impiety alone, but impudency. Lastly his cosenage in shifting of hands giuing one thing for the other. <hi>Ecclesia Dei non habet talem consuetudinē. Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sia dei,</hi> the church of God is one thing, and <hi>Ecelesiapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pae,</hi> the church of the pope is an other thing. In the <hi>ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiuocation</hi> of the church consisteth all the cosenage of all their fallacies. Still they crie vpon the church; meaning their owne church, but pretending Gods church. But we must learne to distinguish them, and so to answere to his Stephanus obiection. <hi>Ecclesia dei non habet talem consuetudinem,</hi> the church of God hath no such custome; wee acknowledge th' authoritie suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and subscribe thereunto. But the church of Rome is not the church of God; and therefore it is not greatly materiall what custome it hath.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="motive">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:2352:47"/>
               <head>The motiue.</head>
               <q>
                  <hi>SO</hi> Luther <hi>and</hi> Zwinglius, <hi>and the rest of that crewe were at the first appearing branded by this note for heretiques. Neither are they able to proue that either ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke or heretique did challenge the church of Rome for any of the controuerted questions. When first they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to arise from</hi> Arius, Aerius, Vigilantius, Berengari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, <hi>and the rest spake against those pointes of doctrine, which wee haue proofe by the aduersaries consent to haue beene practised many ages before in the church. But if they cannot shewe neither in all, nor in one question betweene vs that the repugnance and reiecting of it by any is anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, as the allowance thereof, it is manifest that the latter, not the former, were heretiques which brouhht in al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration.</hi>
               </q>
               <div type="remove">
                  <head>The remoue.</head>
                  <p>SO shamelesse are they in their shameful practises, that the mischiefe which their malice hath concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, their vanity will not haue concealed. So <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Zuinglius,</hi> men great in learning made so much the greater as they were greatly enuied of them; <hi>and the rest of that crewe,</hi> wordes of disdaine come from the hart of pride; <hi>were at the first appearing,</hi> that was short warning, <hi>branded by this note for heretiques:</hi> Let them looke to themselues, who branded them I maruaile? for mee thinketh I see the marke of the beast in their right handes and forheades: in their right handes, for they be ful of bloud; in their forheads for they be ful of falshood. <hi>I but yet none either catholicke or heriticke did
<pb facs="tcp:2352:48"/>challenge the church of Rome for the controuerted questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;</hi> if they did not it was more for feare of <hi>Pauls</hi> sword then <hi>Peters</hi> keyes. And say they were so cunning iug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers that none did espie them as they crept in by little and little with their packe of knauery: yet doth not this therefore excuse them, when as the Apostle cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the raigne of Antichrist the mysterie of iniquitie working secretlie. And yet not so secretly but some haue seene it. Hath not one pope challenged ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? Hath not one papist charged another? and haue not those worthy men of God, <hi>Luther, Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin, Bucer, Peter Martyr, Iewell, Zanchius,</hi> and the rest of Christs sworne soldiours so torne their coates for these controuersies, that their bowelles yet bleede with their wounds? But these bee but vpstartes: which of the ancient did euer reiecte? Which of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers did not wholy allowe euery pointe of popery? First for the supremacy of the Pope ouer other bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops: the repugnance is as ancient as the beginning therof. Nay before it began at Rome your owne <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> condemned it in Constantinople, <hi>vt supra. Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brose, Chrysostome</hi> and <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> no babes: yet these giue sentence with <hi>Gregory</hi> against the superioritie &amp; tiranny of one bishop ouer an other. Which is more odious ouer princes: and yet all their strength is in this. For the name of the church beareth out all their absur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities: &amp; the authority of the Pope doth countenance the church. To come from policy to religion: because you challenge allowance from the fathers, where shall you find so much as the name of the Masse in all the huge Volumes of saint <hi>Augustine?</hi> your placing of images in the church, and worshipping of them, was condemned in an auncient generall councell. And to
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:2352:48"/>let many other questions alone; read bishop Bilson his booke of the true difference of Christian subiection,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Parte</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 776 <hi>Chry. hom.</hi> 43. <hi>in Ihon. Ambrose de ijs qui initiantur myst. cap.</hi> 9 <hi>Aug. de ver. dom in Lu. ser.</hi> 33. <hi>Cyprian de caena Leo. dist.</hi> 2. <hi>Athanasius in illud quicunque dixerit verbum. &amp;c. Irenaeus, lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Aug. Cont. Pel. Aug. Cont. Par.</hi>
                     </note> and vnchristian rebellion, and you shall see all the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers marshalled by him in such good order, against your transubstantiation: that the very throng of them maketh such resistance, that there is no possibilitie of passage that way. <hi>Eutiches</hi> an heretique as all confesse, and yet their transubstantiation the very substance of his opinion: as hee learnedly proueth. That is a small matter: they haue a spice of all heresies. The worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of the crosse took his beginning as part of <hi>Valen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> his heresie. Merit and free will <hi>Pelagian.</hi> Many me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatours <hi>Parmenion:</hi> and all this is popery. In the <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charist</hi> they are <hi>Eutichistes.</hi> In the Crosse <hi>Valentini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</hi> In freewill and merits <hi>Pelagians.</hi> In auouching of many mediatours <hi>Parmenians.</hi> So that to conclude, such is their religion so fraught with the dregs of all heresies, that what father soeuer writ any thing against any heresie: hee must needes write some thing against popery.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>A MOTION ANEXED TO THE MOTIVES AS I found it in my copy.</head>
            <div type="motive">
               <q>
                  <hi>THis (as it is by the Papistes giuen forth) is the worke of Doctor Alablaster, a great clarke (as they say) &amp; an excellent diuine, who (by meanes of priuate conference with a certain seminary priest, whom in prison be labored to conuert) was by the same priest peruerted, so that of a perfect protestant, hee is nowe become an absolute papist, and is for the same imprisoned.</hi>
               </q>
               <div type="remove">
                  <pb facs="tcp:2352:49"/>
                  <head>The remooue.</head>
                  <p>IF these be, as well they may be, the writings of <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Alablaster,</hi> a yong maister of artes, then may they carie some name of wit but no credit of dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion; some smackering of tongues, but small taste of artes; some rubble of Philology, but fewe grounds of Philosophy; some shewe of humanitie, but no sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of Diuinity. And as for the manner of his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stacy or backsliding, the priest himselfe, nay the partie himselfe, nay we our selues know to be farre otherwise then they woulde faine here beare vs in hande. The priest confessed that hee founde him more forwarde, meaning more backwarde, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> more for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly backward then hee could desire: He himselfe confessed, it was a certain ten penny book that helped him to his two penny faith: But wee that know him, know the true cause to be vnthankfulnes banquetting with lust and ambition: For hauing alwaies a great deale more then hee deserued, and yet desiring still, much more then he had, growing discontent with ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, hee fell at ods with faithfulnes.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:2352:49"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>